<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love without interest, or, The man too hard for the master a comedy : as it was acted at the Theatre Royal by His Majesty's servants.</title>
            <author>Pinkethman, William, d. 1725.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19553</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13059556</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13059556</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54093)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 395:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love without interest, or, The man too hard for the master a comedy : as it was acted at the Theatre Royal by His Majesty's servants.</title>
                  <author>Pinkethman, William, d. 1725.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Arthur Bettesworth ... and Richard Ellison ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ascribed to William Pinkethman. Cf. Baker, Biog. dram.; BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Love without Intereſt:</hi> OR, The Man too hard for the Maſter. A COMEDY. As it was Acted at the Theatre Royal, BY His Majeſty's SERVANTS.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fallite fallentes ex magna parte profanum,</l>
               <l>Sunt genus in laqueos quos poſuere cadant.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ovid de Art. Amand. lib. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Arthur Betteſworth,</hi> at the <hi>Red Lion</hi> on <hi>London-Bridge;</hi> and <hi>Richard Elliſon,</hi> at the <hi>Eagle and Child</hi> in the <hi>Pell-Mell,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO
<list>
                  <item>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Lord <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Lord <hi>Jefferies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Lord <hi>Widdrington.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Lord <hi>Buckingham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Lord <hi>James Howard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> the Lord <hi>John Howard.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
TO
<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Tho. Barnardiston,</hi> Bar.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Hugh Smithſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Walters,</hi> Bar.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George Umble,</hi> Bar.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Charles Sidley,</hi> Bar.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Charles Inglefield,</hi> Bar.</item>
               </list>
To
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nahaniel Barnardiſton,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho. Bull,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>— Buller,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Capt. <hi>Buller,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>—Coventry,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Capt. <hi>Campthorne,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ellis Criſp,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Hilyard,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>James Jerras,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Lawley,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ralph Lee,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Litton,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Minſhell,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Luke Norton, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peter Pheaſant, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Pitt, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Colonel <hi>Rumhall, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Roper, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Saywell, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Simon Scroop, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Waſhington Sherley, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paris Slater, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charles Tryon, </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Watſon,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>Eſquires.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS long and laudable Cuſtom bears the Force of a Law, by virtue of which, every Minor Scribler, even the pooreſt Dabler in Dramaticks, lays his Brat at ſome Great Man's Door: In Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge therefore of my Native Engliſh Liberty, I take the Privilege of this preſent Dedication. 'Tis true, the general Claſs of Paper-dawbers have hitherto arrived at no higher Confidence, than affixing ſome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Great Name to a Play; whilſt I, by a bolder Aſſurance (poſſibly a little more pardonable in a Comedian) have here marſhall'd a whole Roll of Quality in my Frontiſpiece.</p>
            <p>Truly, Gentlemen, in this Preſumption I know not what Treſpaſs I may have made in Good Manners; however the World muſt juſtifie my Politicks in this Management. For by this Conduct, inſtead of one worthy for my Patron and Protector, I have hook'd in a whole Battalion of 'em to Champion for me. And therefore undoubtedly this Piece muſt come ſafe into the World under ſo many Shields of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Beſides, from the warm Influence of ſo many Noble Patrons, if (to ſpeak like an Aſtrologer) 'tis a Bleſſing to have the Aſpect of a kind Star at our Nativity; certainly this muſt be much more happy to peep into Light under the Smiles of a whole Conſtellation.</p>
            <p>Nay, Gentlemen, not to be too bold neither, but a little to extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate my Preſumption, I have found out an old State-Diſtinction for a very ſubſtantial Apology, by which I make you All this Preſent, <hi>viz.</hi> Not in your more exalted Capacities of ſo many Perſons of the higheſt Character and Quality, (that Conſideration would have kept me at a more awful Diſtance.) No, Gentlemen, I attack you only as an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Society over a cheerful Glaſs; where, all Greatneſs laid aſide, and Mirth, Wit, and Gayety, the only Reigning Aſcendants amongſt You, I thruſt in my Comick Phyz under that eaſier Acceſs: The Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitable Door ſtands open, and from that Paſport I make my Intruſion.</p>
            <p>Now, Gentlemen, according to the true Poetical Mode of Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I ſhall be very Oratorical in the Praiſes of all my Noble Patrons: But, truly, as my Panegyrical Talent is none of the beſt; and to do Juſtice to ſo fair a Liſt of Honour, in an Encomium upon all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Your ſelect Characters and Vertues, is a Work beyond my reaeh: Nay, and what's another great Argument for my Silence upon that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſo large a Theme before me would out-ſwell the Bulk of an Epiſtle Dedicatory, and conſequently (as my Bookſeller tells me) make my Portico bigger than my Houſe. I ſhall therefore ſhorten that part of my Dedication, and come to a nearer matter in hand, (which
<pb facs="tcp:97016:3"/>is) the Merits of the Play. The Merits of the Play! — Hold a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle— Whereabouts do they lie?— Merits! Yes poſitively Merits, and very conſiderable ones. For look ye, Sirs— St. <hi>George</hi> was the Patron of <hi>England.</hi> (Right.) And he made it a peculiar Point of Honour and Gallantry to take the Weaker Side. (Right agen!) Now as 'tis the Top-Glory of every Heroick Engliſh Great Soul, to follow their own leading Britiſh Worthy, and copy from ſo famous an Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Weakneſs of my Muſe gives her a juſtifiable Title to Your Noble and Generous Patronage; and from that Deſert ſhe claims Your Protection. Beſides, when your Great and Celebrated Authors Dedicate an <hi>OEdipus,</hi> an <hi>Alexander,</hi> or a <hi>Mourning Bride,</hi> or any of thoſe Gigantick Offspings of the Muſes; methinks, in thoſe <hi>Atlas</hi> Piles of Wit and Heroicks, they overload their Patrons with the Preſent they make them. It looks as if a Gardner ſhould ſend you the whole Cargo of a <hi>May</hi>-morning Market in <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> (enough to ſtifle you with Sweets) when, in my ſimple Judgment, 'tis much better (a lighter and eaſier Noſegay) to preſent you with a Pink or a Roſe-bud, as I do.</p>
            <p>As to the but indifferent Succeſs and Reception of this ſhort-liv'd Play, (not to want a Crutch for a Criple) I muſt take the modiſh way of imputing it to Misfortune. Its being hurried up a little too haſtily, made it appear to ſome Diſadvantage in the Performance. It is enough to diſparage the Good Ayer and Charms even of the Beaus themſelves, to appear in too rude a Diſhabilee.</p>
            <p>With all this Plea for my Introduction to Your Good Graces; now, Gentlemen, if, at your next Full Houſe at the <hi>Roſe,</hi> you ſhall gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly pleaſe to paſs an <hi>Affirmative Vote</hi> in my Favour; or, what's more generous, to carry it with a <hi>Nemine Contradicente;</hi> then (to boaſt no more of my own) the Merit ſhall be all of Your ſide; and I ſhall, in all Duty bound, ever ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obliged, and moſt Devoted Servant,</hi> Will. Penkethman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:4"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <stage>Spoke by <hi>Jo. Hains.</hi>
            </stage>
            <l>IF any here dares cry My Prologue down,</l>
            <l>Henceforth I'll not allow one Wit i'th' Town:</l>
            <lg>
               <l>As Houſes, haunted with Ill Spirits, are</l>
               <l>All Noiſe and Lies, ſuch is our Theatre:</l>
               <l>Ye talk of Wits, the Devil of Wit is here.</l>
            </lg>
            <l>Wherefore, to let you know,</l>
            <l>What Wit is not, I think can't be amiſs;</l>
            <l>For no Man here, I'm ſure, knows what it is.</l>
            <l>Firſt then,</l>
            <l>Wit is no Scarf upon Fantaſtick Hips,</l>
            <l>Nor an affected Cringe t'approach the Lips:</l>
            <l>'Tis not I-Gad! O Lord! or, Let me Die!</l>
            <l>Nor is it, Dam me, ye Son of a Whore, ye Lie.</l>
            <l>'Tis not to tell how lewd ye were laſt Night,</l>
            <l>What Watches, Wenches, Windows felt your Spight:</l>
            <l>Nor is it an Abuſive Epilogue,</l>
            <l>Nor being Drunk, and cry, More Wine, ye Dog.</l>
            <l>Tis not your Tradeſman's Wit that makes him Great:</l>
            <l>'Tis a compendious way to Live, and Cheat:</l>
            <lg>
               <l>'Nor is it Wit that makes your Lawyer priz'd,</l>
               <l>His dagled Gown, his Knavery in Diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>To pluck down Honeſt Men, that he may riſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <l>Nor is't pert <hi>Phillis's</hi> Wit that does prevail;</l>
            <l>'Tis not her Tongue ſhe lives by, 'tis her Tail.</l>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis not your Scholar, Traveller, nor Mathematician,</l>
               <l>Poet, nor Player, and Faith 'tis no Phyſician;</l>
               <l>Were I now Clapt, I were in a ſweet Condition.</l>
            </lg>
            <l>'Tis none of theſe, that ſingly Wit can be,</l>
            <l>But all in one Man meeting 's Wit— that Me.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <stage>Deſign'd to have been Spoken by Mr. <hi>Powel.</hi>
            </stage>
            <l>OF all the Fates attend a Mortal State,</l>
            <l>A Poet's ſure the moſt unfortunate.</l>
            <l>Vintners and Cooks th' Advantage have o'th' Bays;</l>
            <l>Wines and Ragouſts as various for to pleaſe,</l>
            <l>As are the Gueſts they treat: He but a Plate</l>
            <l>Before a ſqueamiſh Theatre to ſet.</l>
            <l>What, tho' in that two grand Ingredients meet,</l>
            <l>The Piquant duely mingled with the Sweet:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:4"/>
            <l>A Jeſt to Gravity is but a Clinch,</l>
            <l>And the gall'd Aſſes touch'd ne'er fail to winch:</l>
            <l>Should he purſue the ends of thoſe that write,</l>
            <l>Inſtruct the Mind, the Senſes to delight:</l>
            <l>Yet to your Grand Engroſſers of all Reaſon,</l>
            <l>Mirth is but vile, and Morals out of Seaſon.</l>
            <l>If like a Load'n Bee, 'mongst Mountain-tops he ſlies,</l>
            <l>Like hers his Wings are ſnapt, like her oppreſs'd he dies.</l>
            <l>A creeping Stile provokes Sarcaſtick Scorns,</l>
            <l>Then poor Poetick Snail plucks in his Horns:</l>
            <l>A moderate rate's inſipid too, for then</l>
            <l>The Poet moves but just like other Men.</l>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus high or low, quick, ſlow, ne'er out of ſight,</l>
               <l>Poor Poetaſter ſeldom's in the right,</l>
               <l>The Stragler's damn'd for wandring in the Night.</l>
            </lg>
            <l>Led by you, Stars, the Poet bids me ſay,</l>
            <stage>To the Boxes.</stage>
            <l>He thinks h' has ſtumbled on the milk y way;</l>
            <l>Diſintereſs'd Love, Sincere, Refin'd, and Pure,</l>
            <l>From Sordid Selfiſhneſs, from Droſs of Ore,</l>
            <l>There for a ſpace he hopes to find a Friend;</l>
            <l>Few Nights conducts him to his Journey's end:</l>
            <l>Then dart your Rays, the Poet's ſure of this,</l>
            <l>That Serpents Planet-ſtruck want Power to hiſs.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>EPILOGUE.</head>
            <stage>Spoken by Mr. <hi>Penkethman,</hi> Entring weeping, with a Haltar about his Neck, all in White, and a Noſegay in his Hand.</stage>
            <l>COller'd in Hemp, hanging ripe through Deſpair,</l>
            <l>I come to ſay my Execution Prayer.</l>
            <l>The Crime that puts me in this Fit of Quaking,</l>
            <l>Was turning Fool, and gravely undertaking</l>
            <l>To put that Coin upon you, which the ſnarling</l>
            <l>Scribler that gave it me, ſaid, Was not Sterling.</l>
            <l>And ſince ſad Plays with beſt Succeſs are bleſt,</l>
            <l>To make this Play as bad as moſt o'th' reſt,</l>
            <l>I'll make this Diſmal End, that all may ſee</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Will Pinkethman</hi> can Act a Tragedy.</l>
            <l>May Ladies, Gentlemen, and all that come</l>
            <l>Upon my Day (d' ye ſee) want Elbow-room;</l>
            <l>May Beaus have many Ladies to admire 'em,</l>
            <l>And may the Masks prove kind as they deſire 'em:</l>
            <l>May every Female caſt ſoft Looks upon 'em,</l>
            <l>Taylors and Perriwig-makers never dun 'em.</l>
            <l>But hold, to make an end of my Haranguing,</l>
            <l>Since Company's ne're wanting at a Hanging.</l>
            <l>A Lucky Thought has chang'd my Reſolution,</l>
            <l>Till my own Day I'll put off Execution.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:97016:5"/>
            <head>Dramatis Perſonae.</head>
            <list>
               <label>MEN.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wildman,</hi> A Spark of the Town, whoſe Eſtate Sir <hi>Fickle</hi> has in Mortgage, Suitor to <hi>Letitia.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Powell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Trulove,</hi> A Noble-minded Generous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but of a ſlender Fortune; in Love with <hi>Honoria.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Mills.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sir <hi>Fickle Cheat.</hi> A Cheating, Amorous, Inconſtant, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Old Citizen. By Mr. <hi>Bullock.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jonathan,</hi> A ſly Rogue his Man, but very bold with his Maſter; in League with <hi>Jenny.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Penkethman</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wrangle,</hi> A paſſionate News-talker, a great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to Learning; one that carries all by hard Words miſapply'd. By Mr. <hi>Johnſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Soberſides,</hi> His Counterpeice, a Formal, Magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial ſort of a Man, and a pretended Sceptick. By Mr. <hi>Newth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lurcher,</hi> Servant to <hi>Wildman.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Kent.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>WOMEN.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eugenia,</hi> A cunning Jilt kept by <hi>Wildman,</hi> whom he topps upon Sir <hi>Fickle.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Kent.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Letitia,</hi> A Buxom, Witty, Airy Lady, Niece to <hi>Fickle,</hi> ſecretly in Love with <hi>Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Verbruggen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Honoria,</hi> A Lady of a Mild and Honourable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, her Siſter, in Love with <hi>Trulove.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Rogers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jenny.</hi> Maid to both. Mrs. <hi>Wilkins.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Muſick, Dancers, Bayliffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97016:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Love without Intereſt:</hi> OR, The Man too hard for the Maſter.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I. SCENE Wildman's <hi>Lodgings.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Wildman, Eugenia <hi>following him fawningly.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>NAY, prithee, Girl, retire and leave me; thou e'en cloy'ſt me with thy Kindneſs, by my Life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, Sir; your Oaths are as unſeaſonable as your Words unneceſſary; I can as well believe you without the one, as by the Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Mien gueſs at the other. But you Sparks of the Town uſe us as you do your Hacks, ride us till you tire or gall, then turn us looſe on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And reaſon good, Girl; your true Punk, like your Bird of Prey, pines if conſin'd; but at Liberty ſhifts for its ſelf, and thrives on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>By my Injuries, rather than thus be the ſlighted Subject of your nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rallery, I'll truſt to Chance, and venture on my own bottom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Th' Adventure's ſmall, if any; for you Limberhamm'd Ladies have this of certainty with the Dice, Caſt ye as we pleaſe, Cube-like, you'll be ſure to fall plum on your bottoms, as you call 'em. Well, Wench, Rallery apart then; it ſhall go very hard, if I find not ſome Cully or other to top thee on: In the Interim, I muſt go viſit old <hi>Fickle,</hi> leſt he ſhould me; which if he does firſt, he's eldeſt hand, and then ten to one but he beats me out of my little tho' laſt remaining Stake.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Lurcher.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lurch.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, Here's Sir <hi>Fickle Cheat</hi> deſires to ſpeak with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Fickle?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lurch.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Parthean</hi> Golden Cordial throttle him! Didſt tell him I was within?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lurch.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Sir; you left no Orders to the contrary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Pox o' my Improvidence! But ſhew him up. <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Lurch.</stage> Well, what's ſaid in jeſt of the Devil, I ſee, is literally true of theſe griping Citizens, no ſooner ſpoken of but they appear.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97016:6"/>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I'll be ſworn, they never want your good Word: I wonder at you thus to abuſe Men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Men! Monſters rather. Why, I tell thee, Girl, they're ſuch Auimals, that were <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> alive agen, the Impoſſibility of comprehending their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, would make him duck himſelf a ſecond time in <hi>Fleet-ditch,</hi> as he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Eurippus,</hi> for a far leſs Difficulty in my Mind, Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>So that I muſt not ask you to—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Define 'em! No. To deſcribe 'em you may, and that too's intricate enough: For you muſt know there's as great a difference 'twixt heard and heard in the City, as there is in the Foreſt. But your common Breed are a ſort of Stag-headed, Hen-hearted, Harpy-claw'd Animals.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>A pretty kind of Deſcription truly. But Sir <hi>Fickle,</hi> is he of this kind?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>No, nor of any elſe, Faith; he's an unnatural kind of a Mongrel: For tho he be a Calf of Sixty odd, he's not ſo much as Velvet-headed yet: If he had, 'tis ſuch a Raſcal, he ſhould have been fray'd, burniſh'd, and full-ſumm'd I'faith, before this: I would have taken that Care of his Advancement. So—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Fickle, Jonathan <hi>behind him;</hi> Wild. <hi>runs and embraces Sir</hi> Fickle.</stage>
               <p>Sir <hi>Fickle Cheat!</hi> The welcomeſt Man alive! You've ſpar'd me ſome Pains; for, as you ſee, I'd juſt made ready to wait on you, that we might adjuſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs between us.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tick.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly, not to lie, as a Man may ſay, Sir, that was my Buſineſs, and the main End of my Viſit; for I ſhould be very glad to make an end—</p>
                  <stage>Wild. aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Of my Eſtate, I thank him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>For Money's ſo rare, and Occaſions ſo preſſing— In a word, we have have paid ſo much for our Religion and Liberty—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>That, Thanks to our Fighting Peace-makers, or we'd been forc'd ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſell both to preſerve our Property.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Right, Sir; and therefore I muſt deſire you, with all ſpeed, to pay back my Money, your Indentures, ſcotcht, notcht, and in <hi>Statu quo,</hi> as a Man may ſay, ſhall be forth-coming.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you're the Winner, and ſo may pleaſe to jeſt; but my Neceſſities are ſo earneſt, that I muſt entreat a preſent Supply of a Thouſand Pound more, and then you may be in a fair way to ſee an end, as you deſire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>A Thouſand Pound! A Thouſand Pound! And ready Money too! O Lord, O Lord! Why, 'tis more than <hi>Cathagena</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh Flota</hi> can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. Beſides, Sir, upon mature Conſideration, I find that I have lent you more in Mortgage than the Purchaſe of the Inheritance is worth; you've bit me, you Wag; you have, I'faith.</p>
                  <stage>Wild. aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Would I had, I'd have loſt my Teeth 'fore I'd have left my hold, damn'd Jew. <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Fickle.</stage> Why, you won't thus laugh at my Neceſſity. 'Slife, Sir, I'm on the point of marrying a Fortune, capable both to redeem and to add to my Eſtate; 'tis but a little Money to ſquander amongſt her Servants (as the Cuſtom is, you know) and ſwup, I lick her up as you do a Race of Ginger faſting.</p>
                  <stage>Jonath. <hi>makes Signs to</hi> Wild.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Will you ſo, you liquoriſh Whoreſon, you? Would the Tongue of you were out— Why, this is one of the Devil's ordinary Capricho's, rides us on the Spur to Miſchief, and flounce leaves us ſtuck in the Mire. What a Plot's here loſt! Broke like a Rooſt-Egg, juſt when 'twas going to be hatch'd.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97016:6"/>Hang't, I'll try however: If it don't ſerve me this way, it may another: He'll think I love him, and then I'm ſure to trick him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>How now? What, muſing Man? Ha!—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>A little, Sir; I was caſting about to ſerve you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Were your Will but equal to your Abilities, there would need no great muſing in the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>O Lord, Sir, were but my Abilities equal to my Will, the matter ſhould not ſo long lag A-ſtern— But to ſhew you, Sir, how much I ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you Welfare, I've a Crotchet juſt now come into my Head, might poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be as advantagious to you, as what you juſt now was mentioning. But ſeeing—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, prithee, no Seeing in the Caſe, but Hearing: Come, quickly, dear Dog, open.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide to Wild.</stage>
                  <p>O never fear, Sir; he's a ſtaunch Hound, I'll warrant him, and on a hot Scent that you know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>A little Patience, good Sir; let me but conſider a while.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Pox of Conſideration, that Couſin-German to Cowardiſe. Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, quotha! Why, what Countryman are you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Countryman! Why, a Cockney.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>A Cockney, and conſider! Ha, ha, ha; come, quick, quick, mouth it Cit-like.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then, in three words: You know my Niece <hi>Lettice,</hi> take her and your Eſtate back; and beſides— [<hi>ſpying</hi> Eugenia] But I cry mercy; for I ſee, as you was ſaying, you're already better provided.</p>
                  <stage>To Eug.</stage>
                  <p>O Lord, Madam, I beg you a thouſand Pardons for hindering you of your Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but in the City, Foreſtallers, as a Man may ſay, find but little Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. Once more a thouſand Pardons, fair Lady, indeed la—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>An unwilling and harmleſs Miſtake needs none.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>O Lord, Madam; O Lord, Mr. <hi>Wildman;</hi> what harm, pray now? What Miſtake?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>None of moment, Sir; for the Lady's too nearly related to me to be what you imagine. Her Father lately dead, left her to my Charge, with Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue the chief part of her Fortune, which to preſerve, as well as charm her Cares, not knowing of a Family more honourable than yours, thether I was leading her, in order to crave Admittance.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Aſide to</hi> Eug.</stage>
                  <p>Now Girl.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Is this the worthy Knight, in whoſe Praiſe you were ſpeaking of, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Madam; he is a Knight, worthy <hi>[aſide]</hi> to be Shoulder-ſlipt, with a Horſe-pox.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and pleaſe your Dainty Face, as a Man may ſay, I am a Knight, and Common-Council-man of the City of <hi>London.</hi> I live in the City, where my Houſe would be very much honour'd and ſweetned, as a Man may ſay, with your double-refin'd Preſence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick. to Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah, were I but of your Years, I ſhould tell her more of my Mind: But I'm old, old—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>claps him on the Back.</stage>
                  <p>Heart of Oak, I'll warrant thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <stage>ſtrutting.</stage>
                  <p>Hum, hum.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97016:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>In the Name of Emptineſs, how like a rotten hollow Hogſhead he ſounds; would I had the hooping of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Sir, your Proffer is ſo obliging, 'twere Incivility to refuſe, and inconvenient to defer it. Pleaſe to repoſe your ſelf a moment, we'll wait on you immediately.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Fickle <hi>and</hi> Jon.</stage>
                  <p>Now, Wench, what think'ſt of this ſame Beaſt? Would he not ſerve well enough to wear the Horns? A pair of well-ſpread Antlers, methinks, would ſuit incomparably well with his Jobbernol.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Or if they won't, 'tis no great matter. Would I had him, he ſhould have Choice enough, if that would but content him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>A very virtuous Reſolution, truly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me not of Virtue; what's Virtue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Hum; why, Faith, it has been laid aſide ſo long by the Commonalty, that now they ſcarce know what to make on't: But your Politicians uſe it now and then, as a Stalking horſe, to pop down your over-grown Court Buſtards— But your well-manag'd Diſſimulation—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Is a moſt faſhionable Beaſt; that I grant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And a moſt ſerviceable one too, as the World goes. Now, whoever thinks to rub through without it, will be moſt plaguily harraſs'd before he comes to his Journey's end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Or will ſpeed like a City-banker, with crackt Credit, and empty Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers; ha, ha. Now I hope I pleaſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, any thing that diſpleaſes them does ſo: I've ſuch a Natural Antipathy againſt 'em, that it extends even to their Wives, which makes me ſo ſeldom lay in their Neſts. But to the Point; (for I'm yet as far from it, as a Parſon, whoſe Text is Obedience, and Sermon an Invective againſt Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtance) I'd have you reduce theſe ſame Speculative Notions you have of that ſame neceſſary Implement Diſſimulation into Practice; for I'm miſtaken if you han't ſhortly occaſion to ſhew your Arts of Diſſimulation, the Raſcal did ſo eye thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>O never fear: You will ſooner find a Woman without Pride than Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and Diſſimulation. Why, 'tis our Sexes Talent, our Inſeparable Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, our Feminine Philoſophers Stone, wherewith we convert you Men into Buzzards, from Buzzards to Owls, from Owls to Cookoos, and from Cookoos to—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>clapping his Hand before her Mouth.</stage>
                  <p>Hold, in the Name of <hi>Cerberus;</hi> by the <hi>Egyptian Catadupes,</hi> ſet but theſe Female Clacks a-going, and, troll, they run like the Wiſe Man of <hi>Gotham</hi>'s Cheeſes down hill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Now by my Hopes, you're as impertinent as a French <hi>Valet de Chambre.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And by my Wiſhes, the Vanity of Ten truely Virtuous Women, make not the tenth part of one ſole Punk's, in the way of Preferment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor do they, on the other ſide, poſſeſs the tenth part of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Prithee make that appear, and I'll retract.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall: Be you the Doughty Knight, I the Lady fair; muſter up the whole Cargo of your Common-plac'd Courtſhip, if I don't out-do 'em at their own Weapon, may I lie Croſs-legg'd, Toe-ty'd, and Bed-rid all the Days of my Life.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97016:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Seeing's believing. A Match, I faith. I begin.</p>
                  <stage>Bows.</stage>
                  <p>Think not that Impudence, Divine Beauty, or rather moſt beauteous Divinity, which is the Effect of All-conquering Love; that Love-which ſcorns to be ty'd up to Time, but is no ſooner born than adult.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>How now? What out already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, out already! What, this the Preamble for a Citizen! Why, this is <hi>Common-Garden</hi> Cant, <hi>tout peur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then in City Cant have at you.</p>
                  <stage>Lays by his Sword and Wig, and ſcrapes.</stage>
                  <p>Dainty-fac'd Lady, the Flames of your Beauty have ſo over-healed the yearning Intrails of my Affection, that they already begin to ſimmer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my Belly, as they were in a Stew-pan, whence through the Funnel of my Throat aſcend more Fumes, than from a Maſh-fat through the Stoke-hole of a Brew-houſe. Spare then the Bellows of your Diſdain, and uſe rather the Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of your Condeſcention; for if you continue to puff thus ſcornfully upon me, I ſwear by all the Stock in my Shop, Cellar, and Ware-houſe, my Heart, like a Shin of Beef in a Porridge-pot, will, in the Poaching of an Egg; be hoil'd to Titters, la.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, Sir, what ails you? Methinks I pity your Condition, tho' I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not your meaning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah, my ſweet Sugar-loaf, Words cannot expreſs it: A Sign indeed I have would ſoon make you conceive.</p>
                  <stage>Squeezing her Hand.</stage>
                  <p>Now do you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Heaven knows, I wiſh I did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>Kiſſing her.</stage>
                  <p>Nor yet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah the Devil! She'd have him ſhew it her down-right.</p>
                  <stage>Ruffles and kiſſes her.</stage>
                  <p>Then thus and thus. There's but one more that I know of, and its a pair of Queſtions whether he can make it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Protect my Honour! A Man kiſs me.</p>
                  <stage>Shrieks out.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>How now! What the Devil's the matter? You'll raiſe the Houſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. Pox of your crack'd Treble. So, here's Sir <hi>Fickle</hi> come to lend you a Hand, I'll retire.</p>
                  <stage>Retires, and liſtens.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Fickle <hi>and</hi> Jonath. <hi>who puts him by.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                  <p>O Lord! What's the matter? What's the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me, Sir, I'm ſo frighten'd. Oh—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>For a handſom come off, and I'll croſs the Cudgels: I'll in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe, and give her a Breathing-while.</p>
                  <stage>Enters.</stage>
                  <p>How now, Couſin; what, at the old Trade? What Whim now? 'Tis the frightfulleſt Creature—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Then why would you leave me alone ſo long?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>But with what, i'th' the Name of Wonder?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord, Sir, methought—Hem, hem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Igad, I'll never believe that Miracles are ceas'd, when I ſee a Woman in danger of being choak'd with a Lye.</p>
                  <stage>To Eug.</stage>
                  <p>The ruffling of the Wind in your Window-Curtain; that's all, on my Life.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Sure I'm the firſt Man that ever helpt Woman out with a Come-off.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come, a Woman, and afraid of the ruffling of a Curtain.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97016:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Or of any thing elſe, and you were the <hi>Tom Bold</hi> that blew in at her Window. She muſt cry out before ſhe's hurt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Madam, how is it now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Somewhat better, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick. to Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Then, if you pleaſe, we two'll lead on the way;</l>
                  <l>If Fortune hits, this is our Lucky Day.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild. following.</speaker>
                  <l>True, you old Coxcomb; for if Fortune hit,</l>
                  <l>I'll ſettle <hi>Fickle,</hi> and croſs-bite the Cheat.</l>
                  <l>Let's in, and there conſult the ſureſt way</l>
                  <l>To trap this Fox; and, if I miſs my Aim,</l>
                  <l>Let Fortune, not my Care, receive the Blame.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Truelove <hi>leading</hi> Honoria.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <l>By all thoſe Charms that captivate my Soul,</l>
                     <l>By the ſweet Torture of my longing Mind,</l>
                     <l>Explain this Riddle that confounds my Senſes:</l>
                     <l>Your Eyes, your Actions, nay, your Words ſpeak Love;</l>
                     <l>Yet when I preſs to ratify our Vows,</l>
                     <l>You bluſh, and ſigh, and weep me a Denial.</l>
                     <l>Can I give further Proofs of my Affection?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>No, you're too generous to an injur'd Maid,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe only Portion's Miſery and Ruine;</l>
                     <l>Miſery ſo great, 't has left me void of means</l>
                     <l>To make you a return more ſuitable or juſt,</l>
                     <l>Than by refuſal: Heaven knows how dear it coſts me</l>
                     <l>To involve you in my Ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <l>Cruelly kind, I ſee, inſtead of valluing</l>
                     <l>The Generoſity you ſeem ſo much to prize;</l>
                     <l>You tax me with baſe Avarice,</l>
                     <l>Avarice worſe than Miſers,</l>
                     <l>Who, if preſented with a precious Jemm,</l>
                     <l>Would not ſtand gazing, if 'twere ſet in Gold,</l>
                     <l>But inſtantly with grateful thanks accepts it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>True, Sir; but mine is of ſo mean a Luſtre,</l>
                     <l>That by Poſſeſſion, when you've view'd it well,</l>
                     <l>Without a Foil, you'll ſcarce think it worth the wearing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <l>There you miſtake me, Dear; for by my Love,</l>
                     <l>A Heart, like yours, ſhews faireſt when unſet;</l>
                     <l>There's no Defect in that, no Fault, no Flaw,</l>
                     <l>No Blemiſh, that requires the Artiſts Hand to help it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou more than Man,</l>
                     <l>Take all my Vows, with Heaven my Wiſhes ſhare;</l>
                     <l>But till that Heaven I daily do implore</l>
                     <l>Betters my Fate, I beg you'd preſs no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <l>A laſting Shame on that Barbarians Hand,</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97016:8"/>
                     <l>Who from the Teeming Womb of's Mother Earth</l>
                     <l>Firſt forc'd to light that glittering damning Pelf;</l>
                     <l>Money, the ſcorn of noble generous Minds,</l>
                     <l>The venom'd Hook that ſtrikes inglorious Souls,</l>
                     <l>The petty Grain, which put i'th' guilty Scales,</l>
                     <l>Turns 'em 'gainſt Virtue, Loyalty, and Honour;</l>
                     <l>And an Eternal Curſe on him that rates</l>
                     <l>His Love ſo low, to barter it for Gold:</l>
                     <l>No, generous Love is like a matchleſs Pearl,</l>
                     <l>Not to be purchas'd by the maſſie Toy:</l>
                     <l>The like alone can make the juſt Exchange,</l>
                     <l>And the true Price of Love is only Love:</l>
                     <l>Mine you poſſeſs, with yours I think I'm bleſt;</l>
                     <l>Let not that Bliſs deſtroy my Happineſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <l>Forbear to urge, but too too well belov'd,</l>
                     <l>This needleſs, fruitleſs, diſmal Argument,</l>
                     <l>Your Words, your Deeds, have ſuch a glorious Luſtre,</l>
                     <l>They've quite amaz'd and dazled my weak Senſes;</l>
                     <l>Yet while my Honour and Gratitude remain,</l>
                     <l>I'll ſtill be juſt, ſtill love, and ſtill deny.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Jinny.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Madam <hi>Honoria,</hi> I've been ſeeking you all the Houſe over: Here's my Maſter has been babling for you this half hour: For my part, I believe he is running Mad, he keeps ſuch a Quarter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, what's the matter? Has he loſt any Money lately?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                     <p>Not that I know of, Madam; but I'm mightily miſtaken, or he has got a Miſtreſs, and that may be as bad on all ſides.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>A Miſtreſs!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <p>What diſconſolate Scavingers Relict can this be?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                     <p>I think ſo, Madam; ſhe came with Mr. <hi>Wildman;</hi> he calls her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin <hi>Eugenia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eugenia</hi> and <hi>Wildman</hi> Couſins! I thought they had been nearer related.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                     <p>Lately come out of the Country, I vow, Madam: I dare lay my Maidenhead, if my Maſter holds on his rate, if ſhe don't return very ſpeedily, ſhe's like to leave hers behind her, and follow the Example of her Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <p>Gameſter-like, would ſlur that off in a Bett, ſhe's afraid won't paſs currant in a Bargain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Surely you ſurprize me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, Madam, that's not all; there's Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi> e'en as ſweet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Siſter. I muſt confeſs ſhe keeps him ſomewhat more at a diſtance, than t'other does my Maſter. Alas, theſe Country Ladies are the kindeſt Creatures—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <stage>Aloud.</stage>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleſs me, Sir, whence this Alteration!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                     <p>From that which will cauſe, if I miſtake not, the like in you. But to your Poſt, and take this Word of Advice: Our Fortunes may in all probability
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97016:9"/>depend on <hi>Eugenia;</hi> therefore uſe her with reſpect, promote your Uncle's Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and leave me alone for the reſt.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For when a Miſer once gives up his Heart,</l>
                        <l>With all the reſt he eaſily does part.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon:</speaker>
                     <p>My Obedience ſhall ſhew my Love: So Proſperity and my beſt Wiſhes attend you.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And to encourage you, and end our Strife,</l>
                        <l>Find me a Fortune, I'll find you a Wife.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Truelove. <hi>As</hi> Honoria <hi>is going out, Enter</hi> Letitia, <hi>who ſtops her.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                     <p>O Siſter, I arreſt you in the Name of <hi>Cupid:</hi> One moments Audience for Love's ſake. I come from this ſame Maſter mine to be; you know who I mean, I ſee; prithee, what kind of Creature, what do'ſt think of him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Wildman,</hi> I ſuppoſe, you mean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, ay; who elſe coud'ſt imagin? But once more, What kind of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do'ſt take him to be?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, a Man; and if by the little Acquaintance I have with him I may gueſs, bating ſome Flights which Youth may excuſe, and Slaunder en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, except my <hi>Trulove,</hi> inferiour to few or none.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, as for that matter, I ſtrongly ſuſpect he's no Novice in the World. But, 'twixt you and I, I like a Journeyman ne'er the worſe, for having ſerv'd a Prentiſhip to his Trade, ſo he but mind my Buſineſs when I take him to me, I ſhall ne'er fall a reaping up of old Treſpaſſes done in Strangers Incloſures. As for your Compariſon, Faith, you might have ſpar'd it; I think Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi> as good a Man as your <hi>Trulove,</hi> as you call him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee, why?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſomewhat haſtily.</stage>
                     <p>Prithee, why not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, no Paſſion, Siſter; Sir <hi>Novelty</hi> ſays 'tis a Mortal Enemy to the Complexion. Let Reaſon take place; I'll give you theſe: Firſt, Whether he loves you as my <hi>Trulove</hi> me, is a queſtion—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is more than I can reſolve. However, if a Man be to be believ'd by his Words, he's not far ſhort; and the hindmoſt Dog, you know, may chance to be firſt in with the Hare. As for my part, I love Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi> as well as you your <hi>Trulove;</hi> ſo you may tell him; if it be but neatly done, you'll pleaſure me. However, I'm reſolv'd to have a Courſe or two with him 'fore he ſnaps me up, an't be but to ſhew him the difference 'twixt my ſelf and I know who; tho' perhaps he may have no great need of a Whet. But all's one, I'm reſolv'd to venture my Maidenhead with my Affection, and go Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cargo of my own Goods.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Reſolution ſhews your Diſcretion, and ſeems to me a happy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury of our better Fortunes.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Fortune's a Goddeſs, ſcorns the limmed Slave,</l>
                        <l>But Loves, Careſſes, Crowns the Soul that's brave.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <p>The End of the First ACT.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97016:9"/>
               <head>ACT II. SCENE I.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Letitia, <hi>followed by</hi> Wildman.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>AND ſo as you was ſaying, you love me as— How was't? Lord, what a treacherous Memory have I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I'll repeat it Myriads of times; I love <hi>Letitia</hi> more than herſelf ſhe loves, than Zealots Paſſion, or Court Upſtarts Pride, than Engliſh—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Beef.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Dutch—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Brandy, or <hi>Wildman</hi> Flattery. Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Now by your Beauteous Self, the greateſt Oath,</l>
                  <l>By that which knows the Candor of my Vows,</l>
                  <l>My Heart's too nobly plac'd, to entertain</l>
                  <l>So mean a Vice:</l>
                  <l>Cruſh'd as it is, and broken by your Scorn,</l>
                  <l>A truer yet ne'r Homage paid to Beauty,</l>
                  <l>Which if you thus go on, tho' then too late,</l>
                  <l>Perhaps you'll find to be but too too true:</l>
                  <l>Tho' Pardon deareſt Angel if I wiſh,</l>
                  <l>Rather belov'd, than for your Love to die:</l>
                  <l>Then when the Sand allotted for our Lives</l>
                  <l>Had been employed in Miracles of Love,</l>
                  <l>Wonders to moſt, Examples to the beſt,</l>
                  <l>With equal Pace we'll ſoar to th' Seat o'th' bleſt.</l>
                  <stage>Embracing.</stage>
                  <l>Our Souls thus link'd, we'd both together fly,</l>
                  <stage>Lifting her up.</stage>
                  <l>Cut through the Clouds, and—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <stage>ſinging.</stage>
                  <p>Hey boys up go we.</p>
                  <stage>Puſhing him rudely.</stage>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha. Why, what Gallymaufry Stuff's this! I'd undertake a Journeyman Cobler courts not his Doxy half ſo ridiculouſly— Why, what <hi>Puddle-dock</hi> Pettifogger gave you Advice thus to open your Caſe! Or how much Money and Time have you ſpent in muſtering up from the Refuſe and Scraps of Auxiliary Penny Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, this nauſeous Hodg-podg of Banter and Bombaſt!— Ecud, it turns my Teeth an edge, worſe than the Filing of a Saw.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, tho' my Deſerts merit not your Favour, yet my Civility may juſtly claim a Requital: Neither is my Perſon, if my Friends bely me not, ſo monſtrous ugly, as to turn the Stomach of a more queaſie Perſon than I take your Ladyſhip to be. Why, 'sfoot, Madam, I'm a Man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>So Madam <hi>Eugenia</hi> has partly inform'd me, or in Truth your Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering would have made me ſomewhat dubious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>A Whore! Fooliſh Whore! Fire and Brimſtone, ſhe lies!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Froſt and Snow but ſhe does not; for 'tis to your ſelf I'm beholden for this double Diſcovery; the moſt ſhe gave me was indeed but a ſtrong Suſpicion, which you have more ſtrongly confirm'd: But tho' a Town Spark's Caſt-off be good enough for a Citizens Lady; yet her Keeper, I ſuppoſe, is too modeſt, after a Diſcovery, to intrude himſelf upon his Niece; which, as occaſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, I ſhall acquaint him with. So, leaving you to your more ſerious Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97016:10"/>I remain in Expectation of a Second Meeting, yours, <hi>Letitia.</hi> Ha, ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  <stage>Exit laughing.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Meet thee again! I'd rather meet my Great Grandmother's Ghoſt at Midnight in the bottom of a Cole-pit. What Wild-cats are theſe City Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities! I'd undertake to lick a Bears Cubb into Shape, ſooner than to reclaim one of theſe Haggerds from their Quirks and Freeks, into a competency of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and good Manners. 'Sbud, is this the Quarry the Old Gentleman ſent me to truſs up! 'Tis well, for all her Levity, an ſhe been't too heavy for my Pounces. Or is not this ſome Trick of his to ſtave me off my pretended For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and in the Interim to ruine what little Real yet remains. There's it; confound his <hi>Macchiavillian</hi> Curſhip: There's it. Hum; here he comes; the Simile holds true.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Fickle.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Soh, my Merchant-Venturer to the Land of Love: What Chear, Man, hah! What, art in the Road? Art making the Haven? Hey, boy!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Softly, ſoftly, Sir; tho' you may be ready to put into Port, I'm not put out yet; for tho' the Moon be at Full, I can't gueſs when the Tide will ſerve.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, Pox, an you'll not weigh Anchor, whoſe Fault is't?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas done, Sir; and Sails hoiſt, and juſt as I was launching into the Main, I met with ſuch a Vengeance Mackaril-gale, 'twas a Mercy I was not over-ſett: Of ſplitting I think there was no great Danger; I was kept too far off Shore for that, Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>You talk Riddles, Man; prithee explain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then to be ſhort; I made my Addreſſes with all poſſible Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſhe with more Coolneſs, nay, Rallery, received 'em: I complain'd, and ſhe, I thank her, gave me ſome ſmall Reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>As how, Man; as how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>puſhing him.</stage>
                  <p>As thus Man, as thus; and a Wonder too I ſcap'd ſo: For my part, I expected no leſs than a Black and Blew Suit of Second Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>A Suit of Second Mourning, quotha; ha, ha, ha. Pho, Pox; you know Women at firſt are always ſhy of their Favours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Hum; 'tis not her Shyneſs I complain of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, oh, I thought—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>The matter's not great; a Claw or two on the Noſe, as I take it, and a broken Pair of Shins.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha; a broken pair of Shins, ha, ha. Why, what a Devil— ha, ha? Have you been at Football, ha, ha, ha?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Theſe are the Fruits of Hyperbolical Exaggeration; it creates Laughter where we intend it to promote Pity.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Fick.</stage>
                  <p>Grammercy Dad to be, I'm glad to ſee you in ſo good a Humour: I perceiv'd you were in a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Vein, and was willing to promote it; for, in reality, things were not quite ſo bad; but, Faith, 'twixt you and I, I deſpair of carrying the Town; my Ogling Shots almoſt ſpent, and not one of 'em has ſo much as reach'd the Outwarks; and the Train of Bombaſtick Similes and Proteſtations I brought with me to the Siege is too weak to make any reaſonable Breach; ſo that if you don't reinforce, I muſt e'en pack up Bag and Baggage, and march off whilſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97016:10"/>I may, leſt ſhe ſhould fall upon my Reer and rout it, as ſhe has already diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Van.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Heighty tity! What a Riſe is here from breaking of Shins to taking of Towns! Ha, ha. Come, Courage, Boy; t'other Attack: If thou carry'ſt her not, I will for thee, grate me like a Nutmeg, ha, ha. If thou ſucceedeſt not by Storm, I'll cut off Proviſion, and ſha't do't by Famine, <hi>Wildman,</hi> or No Man 's the Word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Sir, for once I'll venture to follow your Advice: Good Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance boggles not at the firſt Refuſal; and, Thanks to my Stars, of that I'm pretty well provided.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Once more at all; and if ſhe fails me twice,</l>
                     <l>Modeſty's Virtue, Impudence a Vice.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Fickle <hi>Solus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Send thee good Luck, Boy, or ſomebody'll ſmart for't, I feel that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Why what a Gypſie Minks is this! She has wearied me out ever ſince ſhe came into her Teens; nay, even with Threats compell'd me to procure a Husband for her; and now I have don't, ſhe flies off. What a Pox can be the Reaſon of it! 'Sbud, he's handſom enough, and will be rich enough too for a Gentleman. What elſe would ſhe have? Unleſs the Devil has play'd Booty, and given her t'other <hi>Item</hi> of her concealed Fortune; which, if ſhe e'er gets in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Clutches, ſhe'll mount and ſhine like a Kite, with a Paper Lanthorn at the Tail on't: But I've a Trick, I think, to cheat the Devil himſelf; for the Devil's in the Devil, if he once imagins a Citizens Foreman ſhould be true to his Maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jonathan.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord, Sir, what do you mean to tarry thus mumping and maundring to your ſelf! Why, here's my Lord Mayor's Muſick come this half hour; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you'll give 'em Employment, they'll get ſo drunk, they'll be for playing on more Inſtruments than you imagin. Then there's the Cook ſmoaking like a Paſty, and ſwearing by his Chopping-block, unleſs you make haſte, the Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner won't be worth a Fig, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Let 'em drink and ſwear on; I've more Care and Buſineſs than they.</p>
                  <stage>Wheedlingly.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>mocking.</stage>
                  <l>Right Renowned and thrice Honourable Sir <hi>Fickle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Proſpect of Dinner does my Fancy ſo tickle;</l>
                  <l>That no more than a Calves-head ſhall I here what you ſay, Sir;</l>
                  <l>Therefore ſtay till I've Din'd, and therefore pray come away, Sir.</l>
                  <stage>Pulling him.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee Hunger ſharpens Wits as well as Appetites; the Fear of it has had the ſame Effect on me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Fear of what! Your Miſtreſs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, I know that well enough; never fear her, Sir; ſhe loves you, in my Conſcience, I believe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, prithee hear me; thou knoweſt how that Devil <hi>Lettice</hi> has been continually at me for a Husband—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Pho! Why I know that too: And had I not been faithful <hi>Jonathan,</hi> ſhe had been fitted e're now. She knows how to chuſe, tho' I ſay it as ſhou'd not. But—</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97016:11"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, prithee, Patience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Quick, quick then, Sir; this ſame buſineſs is the damnd'ſt Enemy to a Hungry Stomach—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then thou knoweſt with what Care I've ſought her out one; nay, with what Coſt —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, Coſt enough; 'fore I'd have ventur'd ſo much on e're a skittiſh Jades Head in the Town, I'd ſee her both hang'd and drown'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Hang'd and drown'd too! How's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Why her Heels on a Hedge, and her Head in a Ditch. Come budge, budge, Sir; my Gurs grumble moſt horribly for Ammunition: An I don't paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy 'em ſpeedily, they'll be in an Uproar. Come pray, Sir, be jogging.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, ſhortly, thus: Whence her Diſdain to <hi>Wildman</hi> ſprings I can't imagin, unleſs ſhe be in Scent of her Fortune.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, Pox, theſe Gilflirts have Noſes like Northern Hounds: But if I was you, I'd Law her— She might hit on the Scent, but I'd ſpoil her for e'er coming up with the Game.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>That, were it feaſible, would help little; for when Women are once in Scent of their Fortunes or Gallants, cut off their Legs, they'll hobble afrer 'em on their Stumps. No, I've a better Method for that; I'll make her beat Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and then I ſhall be pretty ſafe: I'll commit the Writings to thy Charge, and then I'll ſwear in all the Courts of Chriſtendom, I know nothing of the matter; if that will but content her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, Sir; that you may do both with Safety and Honour; for tho' down-right Perjury may cauſe loſs of Leather and Reputation, yet a handſom Evaſion was always allow'd of as a Mark of Ingenuity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Here, take my Keys. <hi>[Gives them.]</hi> And do'ſt hear? Be vigilant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, Sir, as the Dragon in the Story o're the Golden Pippins. Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant! Why, I ſhan't ſleep a Wink while I have 'em <hi>[Aſide.]</hi> for Joy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>We'll remove all ſecretly and ſecurely, whilſt I in and make 'em pay the Pipers.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And to my laſting Praiſe it ſhall be ſaid</l>
                     <l>A Man was once too many for two Maids.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Jonathan <hi>Solus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Why now Sir <hi>Fickle,</hi> you'd think it a plaguy Diſaſter,</l>
                     <l>If the Man ſhould chance to be too hard for the Maſter.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>There's Rhime for Rhime; and if I don't ſhew you Trick for Trick, may I be thought as great an Aſs as your Worſhip— Why, what an Antichriſtian Dog is this Maſter mine, to abuſe poor Girls thus: 'Fore <hi>George</hi> I cou'd almoſt pity 'em my ſelf. Nay, were I ſure of a Recompence for my Honeſty, I ſhould moſt certainly make a Scruple of Conſcience to be acceſſory to this ſame piece of Knavery. Well, I'll to <hi>Jinny,</hi> and feel her Pulſe; let her ſound her Miſtreſſes Inclinations; for I've ſo much Senſe of Honour, as not to turn Knave but upon a Vantage. —So, here they come, Fox and Pack, I'faith. O Fox, O Joler, O Damſel, O Lightfoot; A Boy, a Boy, a Boy.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Fick. <hi>and</hi> Eug. Wildman <hi>and</hi> Let. Honoria.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Come Madam, come Nieces, Gentlemen Fidlers, I beg your Pardon. Come, let's ſee what Entertainment you have for this Lady. Madam <hi>Eugenia,</hi> you're Miſtreſs of all here. Pray do the Honours of the Houſe, it may be your
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97016:11"/>own another Day, or to Night either; the ſooner the better, ſay I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>And I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, hang Civility: Sit down, ſit down.</p>
                  <stage>Puſhing 'em on their Seats.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jonath. <hi>who nods at</hi> Fickle.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>ſitting on the Ground.</stage>
                  <p>Take your Places, take your Places, Gentiles; ſhow, ſhow there. Pray Gentlemen, diſpatch.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Pox of this ſcraping afore Dinner, it ſerves only to ſet People's Teeth an edge, and ſpoil their Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs: Gout and Palſie light on their mangy Fingers! Would they had done.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>An Entertainment of Muſick. A Sonato.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweetly tweedled, I'faith. Now for a Song.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>A Song! Oh my Guts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam <hi>Eugenia,</hi> you, I know, are good at it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Excuſe me, Sir; our Country Breeding affords but homely Muſick; beſides, my Heart's too heavy to—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, theſe Maidenheads are great Burthens, <hi>Lettice.</hi> I know that by Experience. I bore mine about me for Thirty Years and upwards, and when I got quit on't, methought I was ſo light, ſo eaſie— Well, Madam, ſince you refuſe us the Happineſs of your Voice, I hope I may intreat that of your Company at Dinner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>riſing.</stage>
                  <p>There you hit the Point, Sir. The beſt way to lighten a poor Maidens Heart, is to fill her Belly. Go, pray Gentlemen, walk in, walk in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Muſick.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, we can furniſh you with a very new one, ſo pleaſe you to hear it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>By all means. Come, tune your Trebles.</p>
                  <stage>In a Baſe Voice.</stage>
                  <p>Toll, loll, loll.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>to Muſick.</stage>
                  <p>Frogs and Ravens cram the croaking Windpipe of thee.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Fickle.</stage>
                  <p>Who he! Why, the neweſt Song he has is the Children in the Wood, or the <hi>London</hi> Prentice, or ſome ſuch like Ditty, ſet to the new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Tune of <hi>Old Sir</hi> Simon <hi>the King.</hi> But if you'll compound for a Ketch, I'll ſing you one of my Lord Mayor's going to <hi>Pin-maker</hi>'s-<hi>Hall,</hi> to hear a Snive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Non-Con Separatiſt Divide and Subdivide into the Two and Thirty Points of the Compaſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>For the Honour of the City let's hear it—</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <head>SONG.</head>
                        <l>SHE that marries an Old Man, let this be her Care,</l>
                        <l>At Home as ſhe can, but Abroad well to fare:</l>
                        <l>For at Home tho ſhe chance to be but meanly bleſt,</l>
                        <l>Yet Abroad ſhe may find how to make up the reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <l>If the Cuckold grow Jealous, let her ne're be diſmay'd,</l>
                        <l>But feign an Affection, that Paſſion is laid;</l>
                        <l>With him let her toy, kiſs, chuck, play the Fool;</l>
                        <l>The Receipt is approv'd by the beſt Modern School.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <l>If he ſtill be perverſe, and begin to conteſt,</l>
                        <l>Let her know that a ſurer yet lies in her Breaſt:</l>
                        <l>So ſure, it ne'er fail'd yet to give preſent Eaſe;</l>
                        <l>But kill him with Kindneſs then do as you pleaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97016:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Damn'd ſhrewd Council this! 'Tis well it is but Modern. Now will I be pounded to Pepper, if this ben't the Exhortation of ſome Badger-back'd Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der forth, that us'd to help theſe ravenous Wild-cats to a Bit abroad, as the Song ſays, they lik'd better than their ordinary Fare at home— But enough and too much of that. Now had we a Dance, 'twould perfect the Buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Hell take the Huntſman that—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Muſick.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, Sir, we'll hëlp you out—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
                  <stage>dolefully.</stage>
                  <p>Ah.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Muſick.</speaker>
                  <p>On theſe occaſions we bring Inſtruments of all ſorts and ſexes, fit for this or any other Employment you can deſire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>to Muſick.</stage>
                  <p>Hark you, Friend, have you ever a Black-pudding, Bacon-Hock, or any ſuch Inſtrument to employ my Grinders, my Belly moſt urgently deſires it; 'tis as empty as your Fiddle-caſe, by Famine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Muſick.</speaker>
                  <p>Black-pudding! Why, do you take me for a Tripe-man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Tripe-man! Why, what a pox, if you were a Gold-finder, you're good enough to make his Lordſhip a Crowdero. Why, what a Pox Goodman Catſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guts and Horſe-hair is the matter with you, ha?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha. Prithee, <hi>Jonathan,</hi> three moments Patience, and then—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>falling.</stage>
                  <p>Here lies the Famiſh'd Object of your Inhuman Barbarity.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Three Moments.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha. Poor <hi>Jonathan!</hi> He was a very honeſt Fellow—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>But of an inſatiate Appetite. He ſhou'd have been one of <hi>Marriot</hi>'s Baſtards by his eating.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Inſulting Dogs, thus to triumph over a Man in Miſery! But if I ben't reveng'd on you both, may I go to Bed faſting, and not ſo much as dream of Victuals till to morrow after Dinner.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>A Dance.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>So, ſo, curiouſly caper'd brave Boys, brave Boys all; adjourn to the Cellar or Kitchin till further occaſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>looking up.</stage>
                  <p>Ha! What's that? Cellar and Kitchin.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, they've ſerv'd Dinner upon Table.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>ſtarting up.</stage>
                  <p>Where, where, where?</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Running out,</hi> Wildman <hi>ſtops him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>No pray, Sir; 'tis dangerous jeſting with edg'd Tools.</p>
                  <stage>Pointing to his Teeth.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Come then, Madam; come Mr. <hi>Wildman. Lettice,</hi> I think I need not deſire you; your late Exerciſe, I believe, has got you your Stomach.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Advance, I'll lead you on to try your Teeth</l>
                     <l>Upon a portly piece of Powder'd Beef.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <l>Then there's ſome Hopes at laſt, as l'm a Sinner:</l>
                  <l>I thought he'd made all Dancing, and no Dinner.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>The End of the Second ACT.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97016:12"/>
               <head>ACT III. SCENE <hi>Continues.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jonathan <hi>with a great piece of Bread in one Hand, and pulling in</hi> Jinny <hi>with the other.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>NAY, nay, never hang back for the matter, but come along. What, do'ſt think it reaſonable we two ſhould faſt, when all the reſt are a feaſting? If this be the Conſcience of a Chambermaid—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>And that the Faſting of a Foreman! Deliver us from a Conjunction! Bleſs me! Why, what have you got there? A Shoulder of Mutton?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>biting and mumbling.</stage>
                  <p>Pho, pox, no; this is but a Sippit i'th' Pan to ſtay my Stomach, till that Covey of Cormorants within will give me leave to feed to the purpoſe. But now I have ſo reliſhing a Bit before me, I may ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to leave this—</p>
                  <stage>Puts it in his Pocket, and kiſſes her.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Stand off, Greaſie-chops, and find ſomewhat elſe to ſtay your Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach with then—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>What? Then a Chop of Mutton? Why, 'tis the Staple Diſh, the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler feeds as well on that as the Czar. Ah, a Hind-Quarter of Young Mutton for my Money.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, for your Money, and enough too. I believe your whole Eſtate will ſcarce purchaſe the Carcaſe; but if ever you have me for better for worſe, ſuch courſe Fare as that will never ſerve turn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Sfoot, what woud'ſt have? A Phoenix ſtew'd in Nectar, <hi>Phenicoptero's</hi> Tongues, <hi>Ortolan's</hi> Brains, or any ſuch Kickſhaw. Speak but the word there, thine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no; I have enough for one while, with your Chop of Mutton, as you call it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>A Chambermaid and ſatisfy'd! Nay, then Larks will be good cheap; but tho thou'rt ſo reaſonable, yet I'm bound in honour to—</p>
                  <stage>Offers to kiſs her.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Stand off, I ſay, Pepper and Ginger, or I'll call my Maſter, and have you infus'd in a Hog-trough, where you may cool your Courage as you feed to the purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, you proud Minx; do you make a Bore of me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly, your Snout and Grunting would ſomewhat incline me, did not your long Ears and ſhallow Brains convince me that you're of another Species.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Y'abuſive Jade, theſe Brains that you call ſhallow; ſhall, if you pleaſe, produce a Maſterpiece, and make thee ſhine in Silk and Sattin, <hi>Jinny.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I've had a Crop this day, let that ſuffice:</l>
                     <l>Thou'rt the poor Fool, I only rich and wiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>O rare <hi>Jonathan!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>O true Woman! Who for two or three Nonſenſical Bombaſtick gingling Rhimes, will beſtow on a grunting Swine-ſnouted, long-eard, ſhallow-brain'd Beaſt of a Beau, the Epithet to <hi>Ben Johnſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Igad, an you go on at this rate, I ſhall rather eſteem you a Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Wit, than a Citizen's Foreman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>T'other ſuch word, and Empires, they are thine. Hang petty Lordſhips, I'm for Kingdoms vaſt. I ſay, within this Pouch lie Keys that lock more Riches up, than <hi>Craeſus</hi> e're poſſeſs'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97016:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Gad, the Rogue's elevated; there muſt be ſomewhat in this—Pho, now you think to make a mighty Secret of what I know as well as your ſelf: But 'tis the Trick of your Sex to whiſper Proclamations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>And of yours to proclaim Secrets. Now will I be dock'd, if there ever was, is, or will be that <hi>Arcana</hi> in Nature, that you don't pretend to as full a Knowledge of, as any—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Of you, and with as much Reaſon in my Mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Why there's the Buſineſs. Now will I work a Miracle, and convince you: Prithee tell me but one thing; it belongs to your Trade; ſo far I'll aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you <hi>paravance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, if it belong to my Occupation, I can tell you twenty: What is't?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, the Shape and Size of Mother <hi>Eve</hi>'s green Apron.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>There, I muſt confeſs, you've puzled me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Thy Ingenuity would almoſt make a Man ſuſpect thy Sex. Now will I ſhew you a Quaking Taylor here hard by, who, without Chalk or Yard, and only by his Inward Light, ſhall give you the Dimenſions of it with as great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition and Exactneſs, as if 'twere lying on his Shop-board before him: Or as you would do your own with your nimble Fingers and Picked Elbow there.</p>
                  <stage>Meaſuring from his Fingers end to his Elbow.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Would I had a Glimpſe on't, that I might prye into this Myſtery you keep ſuch a Fuſs withall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Confeſs and recant, and ſomewhat may be done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I do my Preſumption; as for thy Secreſie, 'tis Woman-Proof, I acknowledge it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then here ſtands honeſt <hi>Jonathan</hi> a Grocer's Foreman, that can boaſt of more than the French King and his whole Cabinet Council, who are all led by the Noſe by a She Bearward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay; but prithee unravel what it is?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <l>That that ſhall make thy Miſtreſſes to obtain,</l>
                  <l>Strive to out-vie thy Maſter in their Gifts:</l>
                  <l>Thus fix'd I'll ſtand, while they offer Gold by Pecks,</l>
                  <l>And unregarded ſlight 'em like—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny.</speaker>
                  <p>A Fool in Folio; would you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Gad, ſo I ſhould; the Jade's in the right on't. But this ſame High-flown Language is ſo pretty, it makes a Man ſo Heroick, ſo like a Player. As for Example now:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Huſſey, I ſay, your Miſtreſſes would not dare</l>
                     <l>T'affront me thus as you do, for their Ears.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jinny</speaker>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>My Miſtreſſes again! Igad I have it. Come, Faith, now I gueſs it; my Maſter has intruſted thee with ſomewhat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>With ſomewhat! Why, there are you as far out of the way again, as when you're mumbling your Prayers, and meditating of Miſchief—With ſomewhat, quotha! With all, I ſay; mark that: Once more I ſay, with all; and 'mongſt the reſt, with your Miſtreſſes Fortunes, their Father's Will and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, <hi>cum multis aliis,</hi> enough to bulge a Wheelbarrow. What ſay'ſt now, my <hi>Preſter Joan,</hi> ſhall I make my Words good, ha—Come, ſhall us to <hi>Pontack</hi>'s?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97016:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>And fling the Sop to the Fidlers</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreed; there, Blind Harpers, tak't among you. But t'other Bite.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, twenty. Now if this be true, I'm thine as faſt as Love can make me.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>'Tis good ſtriking now the Iron's hot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>A Match, I faith; there's one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>But, my dear <hi>Jonathan,</hi> thou muſt be honeſt tho'.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>O ne'er fear that's my way: If the Ladies do but outbid my Maſter a Teaſter, they ſhall e'en have 'em; I'll ſhew 'em I can be juſt— But here a comes with a full Paunch, and empty Pate, the only two Diſtinctions 'twixt an <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Burgher and a Citizen of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Then let's away, and remember not a Word by our Loves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, never fear; I ſhall find other Employment for my Tongue than tattling.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Fickle, <hi>and</hi> Eugenia; Wildman, <hi>and</hi> Letitia; Honoria, <hi>as from Dinner.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, the Nobleneſs of your Entertainment has ſo far exceeded Thanks, 'twere vain to think of any other Return than that of admiring your Bounty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle,</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Poor Rogue! I warrant her Holiday Feaſt in the Country was but Bacon and Bagpudding at the beſt.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Eug.</stage>
                  <p>Madam, the leaſt of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours is a ſufficient Reward; but Thanks is more than I deſerve for this and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Entertainments I have in ſtore for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, They are far too mean to offer to your Merits; I ſhould think my ſelf much indebted to Fortune, had ſhe lent me any thing more worthy your Acceptance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild,</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Good— Let Women alone for taking old Occaſions by the topping.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Bear Witneſs, Gentlemen— Madam, you have that i'th bottom of your Bag would make an Emperor proud of accepting.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <p>Then name it, Sir, once more 'tis yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Why 'tis your ſelf; your Love I ask, for all—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <p>'Laſs, Sir, my Heart's too full of Grief to harbour the leaſt Thought of Love; a grateful Acknowledgement is the little All I'm Miſtreſs of; 'tis yours, if you think it worth the receiving.</p>
                  <stage>Weeping.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Excellent Jade! How ſhe drills him!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle,</speaker>
                  <stage>whiſpering.</stage>
                  <p>Nay, don't cry, Sugar-Candy, don't cry; truſt me, you'll make me do ſo too. Chear up, Honey, I'll be thy Father, and Mother, and Siſter, and Brother, and all thy good Friends.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild,</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Now for me <stage>(to <hi>Eugen.</hi>)</stage> Come, Couſin, you are mine by your dead Father's Will committed to my Care; ſpeak, Is your Heart engag'd?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <stage>pointing to Fickle.</stage>
                  <p>Alas! 'twas free, till firſt I ſaw thoſe Eyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle,</speaker>
                  <stage>ſtaring.</stage>
                  <p>Hum, hum.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Then thus I give you to your Wiſhes, ſo you conſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Witneſs theſe Bluſhes, let them ſupply my Speech.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Make room, make place, by your Leave there, Gentlemen, that I may receive my Princeſs as I ought, <stage>(kneeling.)</stage> Thus, as your Prentice, I pay my Reſpects unto your Beauty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <stage>raiſing him.</stage>
                  <p>Then riſe, my Lord, my Maſter, and my Husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, you'll kill me with Kindneſs, as the Song ſays in the new
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97016:14"/>Opera: Ay, do if you can; why, I'm happier than the Pope in the midſt of his Seraglio.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>The Turk, Sir, the Turk.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>The Pope, Mrs. Pert; the Pope, I ſay: Turk or Pope, pray where's the difference, ha?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, Sir, I confeſs you are the better Hiſtorian, <hi>Holinſhead, Stow,</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> were Fools to you, I believe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes that they were, Mrs. Hammerſhine, Mrs. Puſpaws; find me out e'er a Stower that ever ſtow'd, e'er a Baker that ever eat, or e'er a Brewer that ever had the firſt ſup of ſo dainty a Firkin as this is.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To Mr.</hi> Wildman.</stage>
                  <p>I beg your Pardon; but this ſame Madam Kicke-te-ſcratch there, with her <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and <hi>Stowers,</hi> and <hi>Hollingſheads,</hi> and the Devil and all, has put me ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides my ſelf, that I for got the beſt of my Friends. Pray, Sir, ſtudy how I may requite you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>pointing to Let.</stage>
                  <p>There's one, Sir, would over-rate the Service, if—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>If what, Sir? If what? Sure I'm Maſter of my own. Come, Mrs. Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-toes, no ſhall I? ſhall I? This, or none. I've heard of your Pranks, you ſee. If I were not in good Company, I ſhould— ay, that I ſhould. Come, come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide to Wild.</stage>
                  <p>Forbear, or, as I live, I'll diſcover all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, your Good Will I eſteem as a perfect Proof of your Affection; hers by after-Services I ſhall endeavour to deſerve, if poſſible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, Sir, if you're for Conſideration, pray take your own time.</p>
                  <stage>To Eugen.</stage>
                  <p>Come, Pruine Eyes, let's not interrupt their Loves, nor our own.</p>
                  <stage>To Let.</stage>
                  <p>And do you hear, Mrs. Fly-at-all, 'ware worrying, or I'll muſle, chain, and to Kennel with you, I will. Come, my Sugar-Plumb, my Mackaroon, come along.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit.</hi> Fickle, Eugen.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, fair <hi>Letitia,</hi> what is't yet remains?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Only to take your Labour for your Pains.— Ha, ha, ha; what, a rhiming again? I gad, I hate that worſe than your Contrivance, for that was pretty tollerably carried on for a Beginner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>What Contrivance, Siſter? what was't?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Why—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>All will out. Now ſhall I, 'ſpight of my Modeſty, have my good Qualities laid open before my Face.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>But what was't, good Siſter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, only to make a ſmall Swop of—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Ah! it's a coming.</p>
                  <stage>To them.</stage>
                  <p>Ladies, I beg Pardon for the Abruptneſs of my Departure; but, Buſineſs, Madam, Buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, pray, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, Good Madam.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <stage>catching him.</stage>
                  <p>Nay, pray, good, dear, plotting, contriving, bantring, wenching Sir, hear but your Indictment, Sentence ſhall immediately paſs, and then you may go—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>And be hang'd, ſo I may, faith and troth; the Halter's all I have then left to truſt to: And by good Luck I've juſt Money enough left to buy one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <stage>over-hearing.</stage>
                  <p>Bleſs me! how a Woman may be miſtaken.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97016:14"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Miſtaken Madam, what do you mean?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, I thought you had been a Beau?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Not I, Madam, by my Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>So I find by your Pocket, Three Half Pence! Why, I have heard of a Beau at a Nonplus for a Half Penny worth of Ferretting to tie up his Breech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, till the poor Punk, at the Expence of her Garter, had recruited the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage he had ſuſtain'd in her Service, which he himſelf was not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, Siſter, to the Contrivance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, that was ſo ſmall I'd almoſt forgot it, 'twas only to make an Exchange of his Couſin,</p>
                  <stage>looking at him</stage>
                  <p>for himſelf— As for the reſt, the bloody Battery he complains of was caus'd by his own Aſſault; he was for forcing me with him to the World in the Moon, I think, to ſome Seat he has lately purchas'd there, as I take it. Was it not, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Rapture, Madam, Rapture.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>I was moſt plaguily affraid of a full and true Diſcovery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, if you blame him for that, Siſter, I muſt tell you now you're too cruel, I proteſt, had I a Heart to diſpoſe of—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>As I have yet, thank my Stars; it would ſcarce be in his Favour: So, Sir, I beg your Pardon for the abruptneſs of my Departure; but Buſineſs, Sir, Buſineſs.</p>
                  <stage>Exit, laughing.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>The firſt Woman that ever I knew leave her Pleaſure for Buſineſs.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>What, Pleaſure! Sir, believe me, you're ill acquainted with our Sex's Paſſions, they'll laugh for Sorrow as well as cry for Joy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>But in her Smiles I read a grating Scorn;</l>
                  <l>Heavens! In what curs'd Minute was I born,</l>
                  <l>To be thus tortur'd with Diſdain?</l>
                  <l>Malignant Planets!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Curſe not your Stars, they're more auſpicious to you</l>
                  <l>Than you imagine, or thine to me,</l>
                  <l>O, <hi>Trulove!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>For Pity ſake untie this Gordian Knot</l>
                  <l>That keeps my fetter'd Soul in dark Suſpence:</l>
                  <l>The Virgin Bride, with eager trembling Joy</l>
                  <l>Ne'er long t'embrace the lov'd, and lovely he,</l>
                  <l>As I for ſome Relief to eaſe my Soul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>What Eaſe you can imagine I can give.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh no! your <hi>Trulove</hi>'s kind, <hi>Letitia</hi>'s coy,</l>
                  <l>Nay worſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay better, Sir, if that her Love you prize.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Letitia!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Loves you, Sir, I'd almoſt ſaid,</l>
                  <l>As I love <hi>Trulove,</hi> or as <hi>Trulove</hi> me;</l>
                  <l>In Tears I've heard her ſigh it to her ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And make the Simily.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Amazement ſiezes me! Can this be true!</l>
                  <l>Yes, it is true, for <hi>Honoria</hi> ſpeaks:</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97016:15"/>
                  <l>But pardon, Madam, if I ask for once</l>
                  <l>What means her Shineſs, mingled with Diſdain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>She doubts 'tis Int'reſt-forces your Addreſſes;</l>
                  <l>She thinks your Heart has been enſlav'd before,</l>
                  <l>And then ſhe well may fear you do not love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Both true to Heaven and you, I both confeſs</l>
                  <l>To you, who, next that Heaven, I dare moſt truſt;</l>
                  <l>Yet may I feel there all revenging Ire,</l>
                  <l>If, this Moment that I ſpeak, my Heart's not free</l>
                  <l>From any Chains but hers,</l>
                  <l>As Infant Babes before they heard Love nam'd.</l>
                  <l>From Fate and Want, 'tis true, firſt ſprung my Love;</l>
                  <l>But by that aweful Deity I ſwear,</l>
                  <l>Her Coldneſs, by a Power well known to him,</l>
                  <l>Has ſo fomented, nay, encreas'd my Flame,</l>
                  <l>I'd rather live upon ſome Deſart Rock,</l>
                  <l>The Weeds for Food, Repentant-Tears my Drink,</l>
                  <l>Her only for my All,</l>
                  <l>Than 'midſt the greateſt Luxury and Pomp</l>
                  <l>This World, this nauſeous World! can give without-her</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Truſt me, your Words and Actions are ſo full</l>
                  <l>Of true Repentance, and of generous Paſſion,</l>
                  <l>That had I Tears for any but my <hi>Trulove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I could ſpare ſome for you.</l>
                  <l>But go, be proſperous in your matchleſs Flame,</l>
                  <l>Matchleſs indeed to any but my <hi>Trulove</hi>'s;</l>
                  <l>Perſwade her you're but what y'appear to me,</l>
                  <l>You'll find her kind, or force her to be Juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>You, as my better Genius, I obey,</l>
                  <l>I ne'er can miſs, while that points out the way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>And may you find it, tho' I miſs my own,</l>
                  <l>Thou Mirrour of a reclaim'd repentant Lover;</l>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Trulove!</hi> Could I wiſh the leaſt of Ill.</l>
                  <l>To one whoſe Love ſo far ſurpaſſes mine?</l>
                  <l>Thus could I wiſh you, that I might, at leaſt,</l>
                  <l>Merit you better, or you leſs deſerve me.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Trulove <hi>obſerving.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Trulove! Trulove!</hi> Charmer of my Soul!</l>
                  <l>Thou dear Diſturber of my Virgin Peace!</l>
                  <l>Thou Ever-preſent Object to my Mind!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Trulove!</hi> as conſtant.</l>
                  <stage>Trulove <hi>runs and catches her in his Arms, ſhe faints.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>As <hi>Honoria</hi>'s kind.</l>
                  <l>Look up, thou drooping Cherubin! look up,</l>
                  <l>Thou nobleſt Compound of <hi>True Love</hi> and <hi>Honour!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh! why ſo pale? Why cloſe you up thoſe Eyes,</l>
                  <l>That cauſe my Adoration, ſooth my Love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>And may the Powers be deaf unto my Prayers,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97016:15"/>
                  <l>Now deaf, when moſt I need their piteous Help,</l>
                  <l>If I don't love you with an equal Flame,</l>
                  <l>Nay, greater, by my Soul, for it forebodes,</l>
                  <l>Should I our Ruines grant, join Want to Want,</l>
                  <l>And then you ſee the Products of our Loves,</l>
                  <l>The tender Sprouts of our engrafted Souls,</l>
                  <l>Nipp'd by the frozen Blaſts of chilly need,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Flames you now think durable as mine</l>
                  <l>Would turn to Tears, your Love would pine to pity.</l>
                  <l>Bat yet if I, which Omen Heaven avert,</l>
                  <l>Should be reduc'd by Love to that ſad State,</l>
                  <l>To ſee thoſe groveling Infants on my Lap,</l>
                  <l>Making with Tears their fruitleſs Signs for Bread,</l>
                  <l>For want of that expiring on my Breaſts,</l>
                  <stage>Embracing.</stage>
                  <l>I'd hug the darling Cauſe of our Deſtruction,</l>
                  <stage>On his Mouth.</stage>
                  <l>And thus ſigh out my unreproaching Soul.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jenny.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jen.</speaker>
                  <p>So cloſe! Nay, then I'm come before my cue.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <l>More than enough, thou exquiſitely good!</l>
                  <l>I muſt deſiſt, for fear ſo great a Saint</l>
                  <l>Shou'd bear within her a Prophetick Mind;</l>
                  <l>Yet, of you Heavens, that ne'er deny what's Juſt,</l>
                  <stage>Kneeling.</stage>
                  <l>My Heart, as humbl'd as my bended Knee,</l>
                  <l>I crave this mighty Boon:</l>
                  <l>Grant me but Means to ſhew this gen'rous Maid</l>
                  <l>How much I lov'd, how much my Soul ador'd,</l>
                  <l>But to requite this Seraphin of Love;</l>
                  <l>And then, as one, whoſe earthly Frame's too baſe</l>
                  <stage>Raving.</stage>
                  <l>To rival thoſe that twirle the ſpinning Spheres,</l>
                  <stage>Riſing abruptly.</stage>
                  <l>I'll grudging yield to your abſtruſe Decrees.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Sence ſeems unconnected, Actions wild;</l>
                  <l>O ſtem this raging Torrent of your Paſſion;</l>
                  <l>Call up your Reaſon, Srength, and Reſolution,</l>
                  <l>With all thoſe heavenly Gifts adorn your Mind:</l>
                  <l>Methinks I ſee through thoſe condenſed Miſts,</l>
                  <l>Through this long, diſmal, and afflicting Night,</l>
                  <l>A glorious Dawn that ſcatters all the Clouds,</l>
                  <l>And brings a welcome Day-break to our Loves.</l>
                  <l>What if kind Heaven ſhould at the laſt relent?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <stage>muſing.</stage>
                  <p>For you it may, for me it never can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>O ſhield him, all ye glorious Sprights above,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Divine Talents are to Know and Love;</l>
                  <l>Kindly diſtil into my lab'ring Soul</l>
                  <l>Such Charms, as may his wandring Senſe controll;</l>
                  <l>Or by th' Omniſcient Deity I muſt</l>
                  <l>Be baſe, yet ſtill methinks I would be juſt.</l>
                  <l>How fare you, Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97016:16"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jenny.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, Madam, or he ſhall be ſo ſhortly; I bring that along with me will cure all Diſtempers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>It muſt be little leſs, I aſſure you, that can excuſe this unſeaſonable Intruſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>O! Madam, I bring that which will attone for this or any other Crime, yet with Reſpect; I think I came moſt opportunely, for if ever Maid help'd her Miſtreſs out at a dead Lift, 'twas my ſelf; I gad, if I had not watch'd my Cue, you muſt have fell to hugging again, for the ſpeaking part was out I'm ſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me! the Wench is mad.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt have been, or worſe, to have let you run on at this rate, when I had that in my Eye to reconcile the Difference.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Worſe and worſe ſtill. What Difference? or with whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, with Mr. <hi>Trulove,</hi> as I take it: He doats on you, you doat on him, and yet you won't marry him, becauſe— becauſe— I've a Notion on't in my Head, but that's ſuch a new kind of a mad Whim, that there's nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Name nor Reaſon for't. Pray, Sir, what do you call this ſame What-ye-call't?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <stage>madly.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dim-ſighted Maid! I'll couch thy Cataract,</l>
                     <l>Rear thy Cryſtalline Eye-balls to the Skies;</l>
                     <l>Ay, there the— Hah— yet higher, higher yet,</l>
                     <l>Through that tranſparant water'd tabby Veil,</l>
                     <l>Juſt by the Star-embroider'd Throne of Jove,</l>
                     <l>The Strife of Honour, Gratitude, and Love;</l>
                     <stage>Soberly.</stage>
                  </lg>
                  <p>There's the Name. Ask the Women the Reaſon they have monopoliz'd that to Quilt Petticoats with, and 'tis Treaſon by the Laws of the Ladies for Men but to tread on Pea-hens Trains.</p>
                  <stage>Madly.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <stage>weeping.</stage>
                  <p>He raves! he raves! unpitying Powers! he raves!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny,</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>I gad, I think ye both rave: This is the maddeſt Courtſhip I ever ſaw; I could almoſt cry my ſelf, to ſee what Fools they make of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <stage>giving her Hand.</stage>
                  <p>Here, take this fatal, forc'd Reſtorative.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny,</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Ay, right; if the Operation of that don't fetch you both to your Senſes 'fore to Morrow Morning we muſt proceed to Hellebore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>What, yet unmov'd!</l>
                  <stage>Trulove <hi>kiſſes</hi> Honoria<hi>'s Hand.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>No, Thanks to Heaven, he mends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <stage>weeps.</stage>
                  <l>See the Diſtemper purging at his Eyes,</l>
                  <l>And the Sympathick Virtue moiſt'ning mine;</l>
                  <l>This ſure, of all Extreams, muſt be moſt ſad,</l>
                  <l>Both by Love periſh, or for Love be mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>There's no Occaſion for either, Madam, that I know; but one retire into the next Room, if I don't give you an Antidote 'gainſt both, may I not have the licking of the Gallipot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely the Diſeaſe is catching, the Girl talks like—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jen.</speaker>
                  <p>Like an Apothecary, who has a Moſt Excellent <hi>Elixir Salutis</hi> within, I aſſure you, Madam.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97016:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Be plain, or I ſhall have freſh Straw and a dark Chamber provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded— What is't you talk of—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, Lands, Lordſhips, Pounds by Thouſands: Nay, Madam, I don't dream, nor is there any Inchantment in the Caſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Defend me! My Unkle turn'd honeſt!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>No fear of that neither; but he's turn'd Fool, and that's as good for your Purpoſe. In a word, you've heard, I ſuppoſe, of an Eſtate left you by your Father, Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> your Unkle has: I'm ſure Madam <hi>Letitia</hi> told him often enough on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>And loud enough, that I know: But that was but Preſumption, tho' violent enough, I muſt confeſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Then hear the Proof: Your Unkle, for what Reaſons <hi>Jonathan</hi> will tell you, has committed thoſe very Writings to his Keeping, and he has them— as faſt as I have him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Propitious Heavens! How can this be true?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me! Madam, go in and ſee; there's Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi> capitulating with him, he ſtands upon ſome ſmall Conſideration, 'twill make the Gift more valid, as he ſays.</p>
                  <p>Lord! how my Heart leaps to ſee this happy Hour!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Heels you mean.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Strike up, I have no Power—</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Dance.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Now, my Dear <hi>Trulove!</hi> Heavens, at laſt, you ſee</l>
                  <l>Have heard my Sighs, and melted at my Tears—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Honoria</hi> would be proud you'd call her yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>The Heavens are juſt, and I am proud to ſerve you.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Trulove.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Hah! did'ſt mind, <hi>Jenny,</hi> or am I deceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>His Strangeneſs and his quick Departure hence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>For Love's ſake, Madam, invent not ways to vex your ſelf; nothing but Honour harbours in his Breaſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing but Honour, ſay'ſt! Yes, Love does ſure,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe—</l>
                  <l>But theſe, at beſt, are but ſuperfluous Thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Or Grudgings of my late diſtemper'd Mind,</l>
                  <l>Which the vaſt Bleſſing of <hi>Trulove</hi>'s being mine</l>
                  <l>Will ſoon diſperſe:</l>
                  <l>As when ſome anxious Pilot, all the Day,</l>
                  <l>Toſs'd by unconſtant Winds, and angry Sea,</l>
                  <l>Would fain take ſhelter in ſome neighbouring Port,</l>
                  <l>And tacks, and veers, but ſtill is made their Sport;</l>
                  <l>At laſt ſome pitying God rewards his Pains</l>
                  <l>With welcome Safety, and more welcome Gains.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>The End of the Third ACT.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97016:17"/>
               <head>ACT IV. SCENE IV. <hi>Moor-Fields.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Wildman <hi>and</hi> Trulove <hi>meeting.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>OH, Mr. <hi>Trulove!</hi> you're as welcome as unexpected; I've had you once or twice in view, but I never, 'fore this, could give you the Turn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Like enough; for I've ſo cunning a Sportſman to deal with, that I am fain to croſs double, and uſe all the Subtilties I can imagine, leaſt he ſhould unearth me, and caſt me out to the Hounds. Nay lately, when (as I after heard) it was you that was coming to aſſiſt me in capitulating with that ſame Raſcal <hi>Jonathan,</hi> your very Tread ſtruck me into ſuch a Pannick Fear, that in a manner, <hi>nolens volens,</hi> I was fain to ſcamper and take to Covert—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>In your Miſtreſs's Apartment, I ſuppoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>You may; I need make no Secret on't to you. You unharbour'd a Doe, I hear, that's like to give you ſufficient Sport without poaching in my Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe, doſt call her? S'bud, hadſt but ſeen her, when inſtead of flying end-ways, with what Reſolution ſhe ſtood at bay, I gad, you'd have rather taken her for a Sangler—But I expect that ſhortly will make her gentle, if any thing can do it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>True.</speaker>
                  <p>Fie! 'tis unmanly, I'd almoſt ſaid, diſhoneſt, to win a Lady by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, prithee, none of thy nice Moralities, and Punctilio's of Honour. Pox on 'em, they have undone more Gentlemen than Drinking, Dicing, Drab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, and all the other expencely Paſtime of the Town together— Take your own Conrſe, leave me to mine, it ſhall be as Honourable as Safety will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. S'life! ſee here they come; Fortune for me this once I beſeech thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jonathan <hi>with a Trunk upon his Shoulders, followed by</hi> Letitia, Honoria, <hi>and</hi> Jenny.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Servant, Gentlemen. Come in, come in, Damſels, here are your Knight-Errants,</p>
                  <stage>pitches down the Trunk:</stage>
                  <p>So lie thee there, my Charge. Pray, Maſters, remember the Porter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>Tru. give Money.</stage>
                  <p>Ay, ay; here, here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Gold! by the Cap of Maintenance— Now to you Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for I ſuppoſe you'd be the Joint-Purchaſers; tho', now I think on't, I'd beſt expoſe 'em by way of Auction.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Wild.</stage>
                  <p>Pray, Sir, do ſo much as give my Maſter a Call, perhaps he may have a mind to ſome of 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jenny.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, my <hi>Jonathan,</hi> prithee no Delays, ſlip not the Opportunity; for the Goods, now they're once expos'd to Sale, may perhaps not ſerve my Maſter's Turn ſo well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>to Jenny.</stage>
                  <p>I know that, you Jade; but I've two Ends to tantalize him, Lucre and Revenge, the two Idols of your Heatheniſh Sex.</p>
                  <p>Well, Gentlemen, what ſay you to the Matter? —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>What, unſight, unſeen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>O, Madam, there's a whole Farrow of Pigs in the Poke, fat ones, I' faith, I'll ſecure you that. Well, Sirs, ſome few Hundreds, or ſo, you may ſpare, for I would be eaſie; I'm not for extorting, not I, upon Honour.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97016:17"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Hundreds! Nay, then thou'rt too reaſonable, and I ſcorn to be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done in that— S'foot! now I think on't, here's the <hi>Barbado</hi>'s Fleet ſafely arriv'd, I'll buy the whole Cargo at a Lump, and preſent thee with it; Wou'dſt have any thing elſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, that's enough in all Conſcience; for you Sparks are large Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſers, that I know, but bad Performers, or the Women fouly bely you: But conſider on't, Gentlemen, a Thouſand Pound a Man will be fair on all ſides.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>That I'll give thee freely, for my part, if the Sale of my wretched Annuity can raiſe it; here's my Hand, ſhalt have all farther Security I can give thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>O Lack-a-day! Sir, you're a Man of Honour— Come, Mr. <hi>Wild-man,</hi> what ſay you? Will you follow your Leader, and leave the Merchants their Goods to ſolder up their Cracks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, if it muſt be ſo, tho' I confeſs—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, Sir, I'd have you make as cheap a Bargain as may be, eſpecially for Goods that may ſtand you, poſſibly, but in little ſtead. Women, you know, are changeable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope ſo, Madam.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>What Bear-like Entertainment is this! a ſnap of Comfort, and a polt on the Pate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>to Wild.</stage>
                  <p>Come, Sir, come, I'm in pain till I have diſcharg'd my Truſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, prithee, Patience; What, give the Gentleman leave to conſider a little.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>That's needleſs, Madam; for tho' I have felt the Severity of your Diſdain, yet your Honour I never call'd in queſtion.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Jon.</stage>
                  <p>Come, <hi>Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love</hi>'s my Security, if you queſtion my own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>I am, I am; come, prithee, diſpatch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>going to the Trunk.</stage>
                  <p>No, no, I'll—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>interpoſing.</stage>
                  <p>No, no, but you ſhan't; fair and ſoftly, by your Leave, Sir. Think not that a trifling Summ, which here is one will ſhare, has induc'd me to this: Know, Sir, 'tis the Honour of the Deed, and that I'll reſerve en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to my ſelf; the Honour and Danger ſhall be mine, and mine alone.</p>
                  <stage>Opens the Box.</stage>
                  <p>By your Leave, Madam, let me peep into your Stomacher.</p>
                  <stage>Takes out a Paper.</stage>
                  <p>So, here a comes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>Let.</stage>
                  <p>Let's ſee't, let's ſee't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Three moments Patience, Mr. <hi>Wildman,</hi> and then— Hey toſs! what have we got here? <hi>Mynheer van dunc van dunc Vanduncart</hi>'s Bond, I think— Pho pox! 'tis a Dutch Man's Bond, not worth a Butterom.</p>
                  <stage>Takes up another.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <p>Now! now!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Three Moments Patience, Gentlemen, and then— Hum—</p>
                  <stage>Reads.</stage>
                  <p>A Settlement upon my Man <hi>Jonathan</hi> of Twenty Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> after my Deceaſe. Griping Dog! What intended he to do with the reſt? Sure he has ſome Correſpondence in Hell, that he deſigns to draw Bills upon.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Trulove.</stage>
                  <p>Faith, Sir, I ſee 'em on the right ſide of the Stile, as it happens.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, prithee, no more preaching; you'll tire my Patience preſently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Come <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97016:18"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Coming, coming, Sir. <stage>(Tumbles the Papers.)</stage> Oh! have I caught you? <stage>(Stands up, ſhuts the Box, and puts his Foot out.)</stage> Hum, hum, hum. <stage>(Reads.)</stage> My Brother Sir <hi>Roger</hi>'s Settlement upon Niece <hi>Lettice.</hi> Ha! Sir, is this it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, honeſt <hi>Jonathan,</hi> this, or nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Here, Sir.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Letitia.</stage>
                  <p>And give you Joy, Madam.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>And there's two; for when the Man has the Fortune, the Woman's his of Courſe.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Tru.</stage>
                  <p>Here, Sir, here's your <hi>Honoria</hi>'s as cloſe as —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, no more Similies, but to work; let's ſee what elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Elſe! What i'th' the Name of <hi>Balzebub</hi> would you have elſe? You'd make the Devil of a Farmer— Crop and Gleanings too! Why, i'th' Name of Avarice, won't a Thouſand Pound <stage>(points to <hi>Let.</hi>)</stage> a Year, beſides ſo neat, tight, convenient a Pleaſure-Houſe upon it, ſerve turn? Enough, Enough—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>In all Conſcience, but only Curioſity—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I muſt confeſs that's a plaguy itching Diſtemper. But if you want a Raſp, a Rubber, or a Scratcher, <stage>(points to <hi>Let.</hi>)</stage> ſhe'll—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes, preter. Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>To th' Trunk, you Dog, and ceaſe barking, or—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I'd have you to know I am none of your barking Currs: Indeed, I do bite ſometimes; I have Teeth, Sir, as ſhall appear when you'll give me leave to employ 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirrah! </p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Going towards him,</hi> Trulove <hi>interpoſes.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, prithee, make an end; for I ſee you will be the Diſturber.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, Sir, you ſee I love to diſtribute my Favours.</p>
                  <stage>Goes to the Trunk, and ſtumbles over it, rubbing his Shins and Noſe.</stage>
                  <p>Madam <hi>Letitia!</hi> cry your Mercy— Pox on't, I thought it had been her by my Noſe and Shins.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Hellhound! let me come at him. </p>
                  <stage>Trulove <hi>interpoſes again.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Omnes, preter. Wild.</stage>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirrah, diſpatch, or I'll be gone, and leave you to his Mercy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>ſquatting down before the Trunk.</stage>
                  <p>Nay, then it's time to be ſerious.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>I muſt diſpatch before Afternoon's Luncheon-time, or he'll have the whip hand of me, and make me languiſh till Supper.</p>
                  <stage>Jon. <hi>pulls out ſeveral Papers, ſlings 'em by ſlightly, while he ſings.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And when I was a little Boy I waſh'd my Mother's Diſhes,</l>
                     <l>I put my Fingers in the Pail, and pull'd out little Fiſhes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <stage>(Pulling and heaving.)</stage> Ho, up, Maſs. This ſhould be a ſwinger by the weight and gills. <stage>(Pulls out a Parchment, with Labels.)</stage> If this been't a Deed of weight, the Devil's in't. Oh— <stage>(Reads.)</stage> Securities for the Thouſand Pound left by my Brother Sir <hi>Roger</hi> to — <stage>(Overturns the Trunk.)</stage> Here, take 'em among you, for I've neither Encouragement nor Patience to ſtay any longer. Oons, here's Money enough to redeem the City Charter— Save ye, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; and pray remember the Civility-Money.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>As he is going out, enters</hi> Lurcher, <hi>who over-runs him almoſt.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>S bud, you blind Mill Horſe, can't you ſee where you ſtumble?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eurcher.</speaker>
                  <p>Make off, Gentlemen, and Ladies, all of you; here's Sir <hi>Fickle</hi> coming this way, and in a damn'd bad Humour, I can tell you ſo much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, then, all Friends, come all Hands aloft.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They put in all the Papers, except one left on the Stage,</hi> Jon. <hi>takes the Trunk.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97016:18"/>
                  <p>Away, away there, here a comes, and in a plaguy Chafe I'll warrant him, or elſe he wears no Socks to Day, I ſmell that alleady.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Fickle <hi>Solus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, now Sir <hi>Fickle</hi> you're like to be fitted with a young, brisk, gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Lady— Marry ſend you good Luck, for 'tis a ſhrewd Undertaking for one of your Years and Conſtitution; and let me tell you ſo much, Sir, there are many in better Circumſtances than your ſelf that would be plaguily affraid of ſore Eyes for all their Golden Thumb Rings. Well, Look afore you leap, And what's done can't be recover'd, are Proverbial Saws as old as <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, methinks, 'twere worth Time to conſider— Hum! She's young, I <stage>(Coughing.)</stage> o-o-old as her Grannum: She's brisk; ay, pox! brisk enough, enough, and too much for me. Then for her Gallantry, the Girl, I percieve, is pretty well inclin'd; and, for all her Country Breeding, would make ſhift, in a very reaſonable time, to reduce the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Stock into a Pedlar's Pack. Hum, methinks our two Qualities agree like Dogs-Turd and Honey; and I ſhould be moſt plaguily deceiv'd, if, inſtead of a Lenitive for the Spleen, I ſhould meet with a Cauſtick for a ſore Throat. Well, I'll to Council; two Heads are better than one, as Neighbour <hi>Wrangle</hi> ſays, and all the City acknowledge him for the Pro-po-potatripes, I think they call him, of Learning and Sence. Well, I'll to <hi>Graves</hi>'s, this is the Hour of Audience; if I can but meet with him in the Humour of talking Sence in Engliſh, he'll diſpatch me in as few Words as a Lawyer his Client that comes to him in <hi>Forma Pauperis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>Changes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wrangle, Soberſides, Fickle <hi>aloof off.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>Fool! Blockhead! Incomprehenſible Dolt! Thou Ox in an Aſs's Skin!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh here he is, and Neighbour <hi>Soberſides</hi> too! piping hot from the Coffee-Houſe, I'll warrant 'em, by the profoundneſs of their Talk.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>Get you gone to School again, and learn the Meaning of the Word Ratification befor you pretend to diſpute the Legality or Eſſential For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, requiſite to the Conſtitution thereof; for I tell you once more, thou impertinent Head-piece, <hi>Ignoratis terminis, Ignoratur &amp; ars!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle,</speaker>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <p>Oh, I underſtand this a little.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Wrangle.</stage>
                     <p>Ay, ay, Sir, ſo he is an ignorant termegant Aſs, to pretend to argue with you that can read, write, and Latin— But I come, Sir, to adviſe with, not to diſpute, your Wiſdom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>Dilate energically, conciſely, and uninaegmatically.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides.</stage>
                     <p>Oph.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir—</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <p>Pox! now his Learning has got the upper-hand of his Sence, there will be no underſtanding of his cramp Language for Men of my Capacity— Sir, I did not underſtand—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh ye pellucid Stars! whoſe Influences are ſubſervient to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience, deconglommerate me from theſe unzodiacal, uncerebrated, circumam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient Gemini.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97016:19"/>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, an he be got up to the Stars already, O Gemini too ſay I — Save you, Sir, and pray give me notice of the next Thunder; I have a Stock of Beer in my Celler.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>As he is going out,</hi> Wrangle <hi>ſiezes him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>Arreſt! <stage>(<hi>Fickle</hi> ſtarts.)</stage> I will deſcend, the Gods themſelves have deign'd to cope with Mortals.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>With Grocers, Sir!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>With their Inferiors far, with Milkmaids! <hi>Europa</hi> was one, <hi>Jove</hi> courted her in the Shape of a Bull, and had Iſſue by her, a Proginy of Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kolds, autockthonical, aboriginal, demi-deify'd Cuckolds.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O Felices nimium ſi ſua bona norint!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <p>A pretty Account, Faith, of the Riſe of Cuckoldom, a Bull, and a Milk-maid! Doubtleſs hence come the Proverb of ſucking a Bull— But, Sir, be pleas'd to hear my Sence of—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I tell you both Sence or no Sence, Ratification is an Overt Subſequent Act to a Precedent Covert Tranſaction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Overt! Covert! Precedent! and Subſequent! What Trade do theſe Terms of Art belong to? What a Devil, do you banter? Or are you a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll be plain: For Example, I owe you a Grudge; that's a Covert, or Secret Tranſaction in my Mind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>Then <stage>(Kicks and cuffs him.)</stage> This is an Open, Publick, or Overt Act or Declaration thereof— Now I hope you underſtand this is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>O moſt ſenſibly, Sir.</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <p>Pox on him! I could give him a Suit of Second Mourning too, as <hi>Wildman</hi> ſays, for Example's ſake, but that he's ſuch a Royſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrang. to Soberſ.</speaker>
                     <p>And you, I hope, have your Intellectuals meliorated when this— <stage>(Points to <hi>Fickle.</hi>)</stage>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Fick. making to him.</stage>
                     <p>This, what, Sir? This, what? I'd have you to know I'm in as fair a way both to a Chain and a Clog as—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrang.</speaker>
                     <p>But I loſe time 'mongſt a Brace of Owls.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Owls! Pox, Owls! Owls in your Throat, Sir; Owls in your Belly, Sir; Owls in your— Pantiples, Sir. Pox! if hard Words, dry Blows, and Affronts, be all the Counſel I muſt expect, <hi>Exit</hi> my Riddle-me-ree, <stage>Exit. (Turning him out.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>(Fickle at the ſame time.)</stage> Then will I leave you, as I found you, obfuſcated by Poetick Dulneſs and Palpable Calliginoſity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Bur-r-r, Buz-z-z, <hi>Gingiber &amp; Lacer Cicer Pepper atque Papaver.</hi> 
                        <stage>(Turns him out.)</stage> Owls! Pox, Owls! I don't know but I may be as good a Scholar as himſelf. Pox! I begin to—</p>
                     <stage>Re-enter <hi>Wrangle.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wrangle.</speaker>
                     <p>And Cimerian Tenebroſity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Hey! here again with his Tenebroſity? Hey, Noun, <stage>(Runs to him.)</stage> Pronoun, Prepoſition, Conjunction, Participle, Interjection; <hi>Haec aquila,</hi> an Owl, both he and ſhe. <stage>(Like an Owl runs at him.)</stage> Or-ro-o-o-o-o-o— <stage>(Looking after him.)</stage> Huzza! Victoria! So, 'tis but a little Reſolution, and theſe Roarers are ſoon tam'd. <stage>(Spying <hi>Soberſides.</hi>)</stage> O, Sir, cry vour Mercv.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97016:19"/>This ſame paſſionate Puppy has ſo what-ye-call't my Intellectuals, I proteſt, I over-look'd you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Soberſ.</speaker>
                     <stage>gravely.</stage>
                     <p>That might be, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <stage>mocking.</stage>
                     <p>So it might, I vow, Sir. Now ſhall I be as much plagu'd with this Fellow's formal Preciſeneſs, as I was with the t'other's bluſtering Bombaſt— Deliver me but from this Piece of ſtiffn'd Tiffany, and if ever I go to Counſel to a citizen again, may he take my Noſe and Ears for his Fee.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Soberſ.</stage>
                     <p>But Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sob.</speaker>
                     <stage>formally.</stage>
                     <p>Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, Sir, what I intended to have diſcours'd this ſame taſty, old, poſitive Puppy about, was Matrimony; I'm a going to be married to a brisk, young Country Virgin, her Fortune, it's true, is but ſmall, but my Inclinations are great; you know me, let me know your Opinion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sob.</speaker>
                     <p>That I believe I ſhall give you; but firſt, by way of Advice, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend not that Poſitiveneſs in another, whereof you ſeem to be ſo well provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; for you ſeem poſitively to affirm that you are going to be married, which, if you conſider the Mutability of ſublunary things, I eſteem that you might with more Modeſty ſay, that you conceive, or think, judge, or ſuppoſe your ſelf upon the Matrimonial Point.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>The Man's in the right on't there; for we're fartheſt off ſometimes, when we think our ſelves neareſt to the Blank: And I remember, Neighbour <hi>Horner</hi> going once to view a She-Tenement he was about purchaſing, found a Copy-holder making forcible Entry into the capital Meſſuage of the Mannor, and ſo flew off; and Reaſon good, was it not, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sob.</speaker>
                     <p>Not unlikely— Then, Sir, as for her Briskneſs, it may poſſibly be Levity; her Youth artificial, and her Vertue and Virginity as ſlender as her Fortune.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle,</speaker>
                     <stage>angrily.</stage>
                     <p>How, Sir! No Vertue! No Virginity!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sob.</speaker>
                     <p>Poſſibly none; for I am of the Sect of the Scepticks, I think, I affirm nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>But I am not, and do poſitively ſay that Man's a Villain that dare call her Honour in queſtion; therefore, Sir Dubious, pick up your Awls, or, now my Hand's in, I can promiſe you no better Entertainment than your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conglomerating Predeceſſor; th' Example's freſh, my Paſſion riſes; therefore once more walk off, or I ſhall Overtly ratifie upon your Morrion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sob.</speaker>
                     <p>Fortune I contemn, Examples I defie, and will maintain my Opinion, ſpight of Paſſion or Ratification.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, Pox, if you begin to be poſitive, walk, walk, my Philoſopher.</p>
                     <stage>As he turns him out.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sob.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll have Satisfaction for this Affront done to my Perſon and Opinion; I'll be reveng'd, look to it.</p>
                     <stage>Fickle <hi>thruſts him out.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, you only conceive, think, ſuppoſe, or believe ſo: Ha, ha, what a pair of <hi>Iſſaker</hi>'s Aſſes have I turn'd out to Graſs! That Men ſhould be ſuch Fools, as to believe that a hard Word, or myſterial Nod, ſhould be the only Ingredients to the making up of a wiſe Man! Tho', I muſt confeſs, this ſame Scipſtick Philoſopher has put twenty Cunnundrums into my Head. Well, Time will clear all; therefore Patience, ſay I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97016:20"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wildman, <hi>pulling in</hi> Eugenia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, prithee, <hi>Wildman,</hi> whither wou'd you draw me? Come, you'll ne'er forget your old Tricks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, old Tricks! and ſo familiar— I'll retire, this Spark may inform me better than Old Sir Grandſire Grey-beard, with his Scythe and Hour-Glaſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>No, never ſear, I've had enough of that ſame hoity toity Buſineſs; I come to read you a far different Leſſon, for you have been plaguily out of late; and for all your Philoſopher's Stone you brag of, <hi>Lettice</hi> has diſcover'd you to be but of baſe Allay: I gad, ſhould the Old Man diſcover the Counterfeit, you may e'n ſhift for your ſelf; I have done my part every way, if you ſpoil all, your Ruine be upon you; I waſh my Hands of it and you: My Mind's chang'd with my Fortune, and I'm reſolv'd hereafter to feed upon one Diſh; 'tis whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt, you know.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle,</speaker>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <p>A good Beginning, truly! Where will this end, trow?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                     <p>For that matter as you pleaſe; I believe you may find Employment enough at Home. If my Cornuted Cully to be has too much, if his kind Neighbour will but lend him a hand, they'll find me both Reaſonable and Civil.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>A very civil Reſolution indeed! Oh, my Head! My Horns are cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>That as you can agree, mean while be more circumſpect; when you have ſpring'd the Woodcock, why then cook him to your Palate; he's ready plum'd to your Hand, ſo much I can aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                     <p>Plum'd! What mean you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, that, that, my Heart miſgives me moſt confoundedly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>No Queſtions, for Safety ſake. Women ought to be truſted with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, as Mad Folks with Daggers; you may give 'em the Scabbard to pleaſe 'em, but be ſure to keep the Weapon cloſe and faſt. <stage>(Treads upon a Paper.)</stage> So, what have we here? Some Grocer's Bill, I'll warrant ir. <stage>(Takes it up, and looks on it.)</stage> No, Faith, 'tis <hi>Vanduncart</hi>'s Bond.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, Oh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Left out for haſt, in the laſt Surprize; I wiſh there he no more: For tho' I'm pretty ſure of my Point, yet things are not yet ripe enough for a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. Let's ſee. <stage>(Looking about, ſpies Sir <hi>Fickle,</hi> who makes up to him.)</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Hem, hem; yours, Sir, yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, Sir, you're a diligent Courtier. Indeed, were you not a true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Engliſhman; one would take this for <hi>Italian</hi> Jealouſie, but 'tis too ſoon for that Man, ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, truly, Sir, I am ſomewhat of a different Opinion, as a Man may ſay; I think it is rather of the lateſt; for—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Right too; for when things are ſo far advanc'd, Jealouſie's as unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as a Song or Dance brought in Head and Shoulders, to lengthen out or ſet off a ſcanty-witted Bear-Play.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Gently, gently, Sir; not ſo neither. My Farce is but a Rehearſing, and I find it ſo far below my Expectation, I'm affraid to venture it on the Theatre, for fear of being hiſs'd off the Stage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97016:20"/>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <p>The Devil's in him, ſure— Sir, you're myſterions; pray, be plain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then moſt plainly thus: My Love, Thanks to my Years, has been ſo moderate as to leave me ſome few of my Senſes, with which I have conſider'd, that at the beſt 'tis but Folly, but in old Men meer Dotage. I find all other Paſſions encreaſing, this only dwindl'd to nothing, which makes me judge my ſelf unfit for a Lady of her Qualities. Theſe, and ſome other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ones, have abated the Violence of my Frenſie, and inſpir'd into me the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of gaining in <hi>Statu quo,</hi> as a Man may ſay, till I ſee better Reaſons for a Change— Now I hope you're both ſatisfy'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                     <stage>weeping.</stage>
                     <p>Oh my Heart!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <p>Oh my Head a!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <l>Satisfy'd! No, but I will expect it</l>
                     <l>For all th'Affronts you've put upon my Couſin,</l>
                     <l>Poor tho' in Fortune, yet in Vertue rich;</l>
                     <l>For all thoſe Tears, thou ſtony-hearted Beaſt!</l>
                     <l>Your Barbarity now cauſes her to ſhed.</l>
                     <l>Her Preſence now protects you from my Rage.</l>
                     <l>But ſet a better Price on Innocence,</l>
                     <l>Or Fell Revenge ſhall follow you with ſpeed.</l>
                     <l>Come, Couſin.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt.</hi> Fickle <hi>manet.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, ay, I'll prevent that; I'll ſwear the Peace againſt him: Firſt, for endeavouring to top his Whore upon me; and then for threatning to Fell me. If I don't, believe her honeſt. Many a Man has cut a Caper, and never come down alive again, for leſs than this, that's certain. I'll trounce the ſly Dog; I'll bind him to his good Behaviour, I will a— O plague of the Devil! now I talk of binding, the Bond! the Bond! how come that there? I'm ſure it was in the Trunk I entruſted <hi>Jonathan</hi> with. I gad, if he gets the reſt, I'm like to be hamper'd my ſelf. By <hi>Cheapſide</hi> Conduit, I'm running mad; Horn-mad, by <hi>Bedlam</hi> Weather-cock. But Neceſſity has no Law. I muſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure my Youngſter and my ſelf, and take the beſt Order for the reſt the little Brains I have will permit;</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And if I fruſtrate all their poiſonous Arts,</l>
                        <l>Why then Sir <hi>Fickle</hi> is a Man of Parts.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The End of the Fourth ACT.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:97016:21"/>
               <head>ACT V. Trulove <hi>and</hi> Wildman <hi>meeting.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>ONce more well met, I've been getting the Writings. Oh! I ſee you're likewiſe in Poſſeſſion, you have loſt no more time then my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Not a minute. Delays in theſe Caſes are as dangerous as Diligence neceſſary. Had I not been aſſiduous, the Rogue might have relaps'd into Villany, and been true to his Truſt— But now for my Spouſe to be, methinks I would ſoon put an end to this ſame Affair; for I ſhall ne'er think her ſecure till I have her in the Laſh of Matrimony; beſides, Faith, I long to give the poor Rogue ſome hearty Proof of my Affection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Somewhat too I have reſolv'd, which makes me uneaſie till it be put in Execution.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>How, you!— Why, you have been ſo long us'd to dance Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, I dare have ſworn you'd have ſerv'd your full time, without repining, to have been made Free of the Corporation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>You're wide, Sir, you're wide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Or rather ſhort, I believe; for you Archers of the Honourable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraternity of blind <hi>Cupid,</hi> have ſuch damn'd long marks, that we poor Bow-men can't reach within a Score of your Butts—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Troth, like enough.</p>
                  <p>But here comes my Snow-ball rouling to way. Wou'd to Chance ſhe'd pick me up in her Paſſage, I'd thaw her with a Vengence, or ſhe ſhould freeze me to her.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Letitia.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Servant, Gentlemen, how is't with ye ſince the laſt Surprize?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Gentlemen, ſure I'm deaf, or ſhe's dim-ſighted.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Let.</stage>
                  <p>As with a hungry Gueſt, when Dinner's on the Table, that curſes the grateleſs Chaplain for being out of the way, Madam.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>O! Sir, 'tis but a ſhort Collation of cold Meat; and there needs not ſo much Ceremony for that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>I know that, if I had but the Courage to fall on; but there's ſuch a damn'd many little Bones in the Pye, I'm affraid of being choak'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <stage>over-hearing.</stage>
                  <p>Therefore chew well before you ſwallow for good and all, Sir; Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Chew, what, Madam? Oons! I'm none of your Camelions, to feed upon the Cud of a Wind-cholick Air.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>But, by way of Paſtime, you might ſtand a little, and bite on the Bitt—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Like a Horſe, and break my Teeth like an Aſs— Conſolation and Preferment in abundance! Trepan my Pericranium— Madam, ſince you have no other Employment for me, than as a Poſt to fix your Jeſts on, I think I may, without Incivility, make bold to retire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me, Sir, why ſo haſty? Why, this is Volunteer-like; ſerve till you're on the Point of Promotion, and then quit your Poſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:97016:21"/>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>That, Madam, you can't blame me for, ſince the Fatigues I've under gone have diſabled me for further Service.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, then indeed I muſt look out for a freſh Man; yet, through Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, I'll not quite caſt you off, but keep you by me. Let's ſee, <stage>(opens his Mouth;)</stage> ay, in quality of a Nut cracker: Your Teeth are ſound enough yet, I ſee, if your Breath be but ſweet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Oons, a Nut-cracker! what do you take me for a Monkey, Madam?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>What, ſtill complain! Why, I've known many a Woman has put her Husband to a far worſe Employment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Madam, ſince you're in the vein, pray pleaſe your Fancy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely; I have done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>And I, for this Bout.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>I ſhall prevent the next.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let. to Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Sir, Penſive! when your Happineſs is ſo nigh. Sure, your overfaſting has ſpoil'd your Stomach; if ſo, I'll give you a Cordial ſhall retrieve it— Here, <stage>(Enter Singer)</stage> ſing the Song my Siſter made t'other Day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                     <body>
                        <head>SONG. </head>
                        <lg>
                           <head>(1.)</head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>HOpe, thou Friend to the Diſtreſſed,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Kind Reviver of the Mind;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>None that Hopes, can be oppreſſed:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Tho' Fortune frowns, thou'rt ever kind.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <head>(2.)</head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hope, thou ſov'reign Eaſe to Grief,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Bleſs'd Encreaſer of our Joy,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thou ſhouldſt have Proof, thou beſt Relief,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>'Gainſt what would my Love deſtroy.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <head>(3.)</head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Welcome Hope, Adieu Deſpair,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The tott'ring Wheel at laſt will turn;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Tho' I languiſh for my Dear,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I'll not conſume, but ever burn.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <stage>Twice.</stage>
                           <l>Tho' I languiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Sir; this, I hope, has ſome Effect on you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Medicines, Madam, are but at beſt caſt away, where the Malady of the Patient is miſapprehended.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, Sir, I muſt confeſs your late Symptoms have been ſo ſtrange, that I cannot but gueſs your Diſtemper to be of the moſt unuſual.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>True, Madam, in the Age we live, but I have reap'd this Benefit by my Misfortune, to find the ſtrongeſt Paſſion too weak to withſtand a generous Reſolution.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Words, Sir, are as myſterious as ever; but here comes your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thollicon: If that does not work effectually, your Condition's deplorable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Honoria, <hi>who runs and embraces</hi> Trulove.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>O, my dear <hi>Trulove!</hi> thus let me embrace thee,</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97016:22"/>
                  <l>Thus let me claſp thee in my longing Arms,</l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>(Kiſſing.)</stage> And thus cement our Hands, Lips, Hearts, together.</l>
                  <l>Pardon, if Love o'ercome my Modeſty;</l>
                  <l>For now I count you as my better Part.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <l>Look down, ye Powers, and view this matchleſs Love.</l>
                  <l>Steal my faint Heart, direct my trembling Hand;</l>
                  <l>Aſſure my fault'ring Tongue, grant Strength of Mind</l>
                  <l>To act that which you only could inſpire.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Gives the Papers to</hi> Hon.</stage>
                  <l>With theſe take back your Vows; and with them mine,</l>
                  <l>May you be happier in a nobler He,</l>
                  <l>As far 'bove me, as is your Love and Honour:</l>
                  <l>Nay, by the Pains I feel, if it might be,</l>
                  <l>I'd wiſh him ſo divine as to deſerve you.</l>
                  <l>Then when I ſee you circl'd in his Arms,</l>
                  <l>Raviſh'd with Joys, diſſolv'd in Exſtaſie,</l>
                  <l>I'll ſend up Vows unenvious Vows to Heaven,</l>
                  <l>To make them infinite, your Loves eternal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <p>What can this mean! O my Prophetick Fears?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <l>I mean you've truſted ſuch a Stock of Love</l>
                  <l>With one ſo far unable to requite it,</l>
                  <l>That it were Baſeneſs, beyond all Excuſe,</l>
                  <l>Still to run on when ſo much is unpay'd:</l>
                  <l>I mean to teach th' admiring Powers above,</l>
                  <l>My Gratitude's as great, more gen'rous than your Love.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Trulove.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Hum— Why, I muſt confeſs this is ſomewhat ſurprizing. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I ſhall rather imitate than diſcommend it— Here, Madam, <stage>(Gives the Papers to <hi>Let.</hi>)</stage> receive your own, and with them all I can call mine. My Heart's diſingag'd, my Affection entirely yours to bragg of; more, would be but to relapſe into what you have ſo ſeverely, but juſtly, reprov'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, now you're ſerious ſomewhat may be done: But I fear'd Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations before Surrender; which, if they had happen'd— But no more, hope well; you know I hear you're not indifferent to me, 'tis with Joy I own it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>This is too much— But ſee the fair <hi>Honoria</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bedew'd, and ſilent, as a Summer's Night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, cheer up, Siſter: What, <hi>a-la-mort</hi> Woman, whining for a loſt Lover, when you have wherewithal to buy a Score of Husbands! But three Days Patience, and on my Life you'll have more Suitors than you'll diſpatch in three Months.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>No; may I live by all Mankind diſdain'd,</l>
                  <l>And die a wretched Object of Deſpair,</l>
                  <l>If e'er within this Heart I entertain</l>
                  <l>A ſecond Thought for any but my <hi>Truelove.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What tho' to you perchance he ſeem unkind,</l>
                  <l>Yet I, that view the Treaſures of his Mind</l>
                  <l>Adore him ſtill, as from the Powers above,</l>
                  <l>Take this Correction as a Sign of Love.</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97016:22"/>
                  <l>Nay, by my fleeting Love-ſick Soul I ſwear,</l>
                  <l>Should he be cold, nay farther yet ſevere,</l>
                  <l>The little ſpace then doom'd me for to live,</l>
                  <l>To th' pleaſing Thoughts of our paſt Loves I'd give:</l>
                  <l>Then, when you'd think that I forſaken lie,</l>
                  <l>You'd ſee my <hi>Trulove</hi> beg me not to die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Cold Comfort, by my departing Maidenhead, Siſter, if this be all; but I hope there's warmer in ſtore.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Wild.</stage>
                  <p>You know, Sir, your Obligations to my Siſter; I need not tell you the Occaſions preſent, to require them, and oblige me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, I do as well as I am acquainted with his Temper. 'Tis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to Obſtinacy, but not perverſe to Reaſon. So good a Cauſe can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want a happy Iſſue— I go with Confidence of good Succeſs to ſerve you.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Wild.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <l>Unhappy Maid! what Crimes have I committed,</l>
                  <l>Doubly to ſuffer by Exceſs of Love?</l>
                  <l>Whom ſhall I accuſe? The Gods? Oh no,</l>
                  <l>They're Juſt, and <hi>Trulove</hi> is in Honour next 'em;</l>
                  <l>No, 'tis my Self, my Frowardneſs, my Pride,</l>
                  <l>Nay worſe,</l>
                  <l>My black Ingratitude to ſo much Love,</l>
                  <l>Has forc'd this unexampl'd Judgment on me.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill, methinks, I did but that which he</l>
                  <l>So lately and ſo ſtrictly did purſue,</l>
                  <l>As if h' had taken Copy from my Actions;</l>
                  <l>And he's too wiſe, nay, too divinely good,</l>
                  <l>To act or follow ought that is amiſs.</l>
                  <l>Heavens! in what a Lab'rinth am I got,</l>
                  <l>Lend me the Clew, or kindly end my Pain.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wild. <hi>with</hi> Tru.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope they have heard you, look back.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <stage>kneeling.</stage>
                  <l>Thus ſtubborn Criminals that Grace refuſe,</l>
                  <l>Trembling when late the proffer'd Mercy crave:</l>
                  <l>Sure 'twas ſome Evil Genius led me out</l>
                  <l>From Paradice, thus to run to my Deſtruction.</l>
                  <l>Yet you can pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
                  <stage>raiſing him.</stage>
                  <l>Unkind! thus to upbraid me with that Act,</l>
                  <l>That firſt was mine, by you but faintly trac'd;</l>
                  <l>Pardons for Crimes! You may command my Love;</l>
                  <l>If in Exchange you grant me yours, I'm bleſs'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <l>Then, ye propitious Powers, ſmile kindly on us,</l>
                  <l>And yet prepare your direſt, worſt, Revenge,</l>
                  <l>If ought, ſave you, I like <hi>Honoria</hi> prize,</l>
                  <l>If next to you I do not her adore;</l>
                  <l>If her, whilſt Life, nay, after Death, I love not</l>
                  <l>With the ſame Paſſion that now fills my Breaſt.</l>
                  <l>And dart it down; nay worſe, be ſhe unkind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97016:23"/>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>So much for that. Now, Madam, 'tis my turn;</l>
                  <l>If I perform it not with ſo much Zeal,</l>
                  <l>'Tis want of Words, not Paſſion, pleads Excuſe.</l>
                  <p>Beſides: Faith, to tell you neatly my Mind, theſe far-fatch'd Expreſſions, and new-fangl'd ways of Courtſhip, become a Stage far better than a Lady's Bed-Chamber.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, that I expect not, but this you muſt,</l>
                  <l>If I catch you in the old Haunt, or any where elſe.</l>
                  <l>But—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, if I elope, bar me of my Thirds. I'm content, as to that Point, to reinverſe the Law, and become Baron-Covert.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>Of your Thirds! Don't ſo much as expect a bare Allimony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And, Faith, I'll ſay ſo much for my ſelf; if we're once join'd, I ſhall ne'er hope for a ſeparate Maintenance— Come, agreed, agreed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>As for the reſt, I bring you a plentiful Fortune; and, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſays, a tite, neat, and convenient Tenement. Uſe me like a Gectleman, I entirely truſt in you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, give me your Hand—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <stage>giving it.</stage>
                  <p>And Heart are yours, from this Breath to my laſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>So, now the Storm's blown over, Sky's ſerene.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <stage>within.</stage>
                  <p>Come, no more Words, but produce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Not yet, Faith, I hear a grumbling thereaway; and I have a plaguy Opinion the Clap will fall ſomewhere hereabouts— Oh, here it comes with a Vengeance. Retire <hi>Trulove.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>He goes aſide, and Enter</hi> Fickle <hi>and</hi> Jonathan.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me not of ſafe Cuſtody, or honeſt Hands; mine are the ſafeſt and honeſteſt too for my purpoſe. Therefore once more produce, or— <stage>(ſpies them.)</stage>— Oh Niece, have you conſider'd? And you, Mr. <hi>Wildman?</hi> I hope your Paſſion's over; How is't, ha?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, as my Wiſhes, but you ſeem ſomewhat troubled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, a little, not much neither. But this ſame Rogue, Dog, of a <hi>Jonathan</hi> would move a Saint— Your Mortgage, Sir, I'll reſign you up, as ſoon as that— will give me leave. Swine's Snout, be gone, and fetch it; no more grunting.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>As</hi> Jonathan <hi>is going out,</hi> Trulove <hi>whiſpers him; and Exit</hi> Jon.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I ſhall receive it with Thanks. One more Requeſt I muſt repeat; I'm ſure you have too much Good Nature to deny me. <stage>(Enter <hi>Eug.</hi>)</stage> Oh! here it is, you know my Meaning, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, the Devil! ſhe here!— Why, Sir, and you know mine; you'll find me no Changeling, tho' you deſign'd me for an aboriginal Cuckold, as Neighbour <hi>Wrangle</hi> calls it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor me ſo tame a Coward to put up ſuch Affronts both to my Couſin and my ſelf! I'll waſh 'em off in thy degenerate Blood. <stage>(<hi>Wild.</hi> draws, the Women all run out, ſhrieking Murder! except <hi>Eugenia,</hi> who interpoſes.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! ſpare my Love, or let us die together!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Die together! No, nor lie together: If ye do, it may be in <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> or <hi>Little-eaſe</hi>—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, Sir, reſolve to—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:97016:23"/>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo quick, Sir? If I muſt be executed, methinks you might grant me a Reprieve. Pray, Sir, conſider; were't your own Caſe, you'd not be ſo haſty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>puts up.</stage>
                  <p>Nay, if Time be all you ask, take it, provided it be Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>O, as for that matter, Sir, I only deſire juſt as much as to— <stage>(Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning off, <hi>Wild.</hi> catches him)</stage> Murder! Murder! Jacobites! Papiſts! <stage>(ſhrilly)</stage> a Rape! a Rape! a Rape!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>draws, and preſents.</stage>
                  <p>I'll cut your bellowing Bull's Throat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>eug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>laying hold on Wild.</hi> O! hold your Hand; for if he bleeds, I die.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>You Lye, you jilting Whore! you Lye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <stage>enters, and interpoſes.</stage>
                  <p>Hold, Sir! What e'er it be, it can't be brave, thus to aſſault a naked Man: If his Cauſe be Juſt, he ſhan't want one to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, <stage>(to him)</stage> Mr. <hi>Trulove,</hi> he's a Rogue, if not a Coward; here I've given him my Niece, and his mortgag'd Eſtate back, and he in Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence would ſtick me like a Pig.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Then hear me too, ſince you will needs be Judge:</l>
                  <l>This Flatt'ring villain! For he is no better,</l>
                  <l>With Gifts, Oaths, Courtſhips, has allur'd my Couſin;</l>
                  <l>And now he finds ſhe loves, he ſlights her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, there I leave your Cauſe, 'tis ſo unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>My Life I ne'er will venture to aſſert it;</l>
                  <l>Yet, that you may not die defenceleſs,</l>
                  <l>I'll lend you this.</l>
                  <stage>Tru. <hi>proffers his Sword.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Lend me your Sword! I'd as lieve you'd lend me a Halter. Sir, I'd have you to know I'm a good Chriſtian, and will keep the King's Peace. I fight! I'll be hang'd, nay, marry as ſoon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, then, thou Cheat! thou ignominious Knave!</l>
                  <l>Know I have found you out, and am poſſeſs'd</l>
                  <l>Of all Sir <hi>Roger</hi>'s Papers, and my Mortgage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Ruin'd! undone! like a Bundle of Licoriſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Not all, Sir, by your Leave: I have my ſhare, and peruſing 'em over, I find an Account to be made, ſome Arrears of Inrereſt, and ſo forth, you know; and look to't, for I ſhall be ſevere.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Accounts to you! Why, what are you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Honoria</hi>'s Husband; and conſequently, as I take it, your Nephew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Over-reach'd again! <stage>(Aſide.)</stage> I knew, tho' I wink'd at it, he was play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereabouts; but now the ſharking Dog has bit to the purpoſe, Hook and Bait, I' Faith, he has clear'd me of my Tackling.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Not yet; but I think I ſhall, 'fore I've done, come in there.</p>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Lurcher</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> diſguis'd, like Bailiffs.</stage>
                  <p>Now do your Offices.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I arreſt you in an Action of Account, at the Suit of Mr. <hi>Trulove.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lurch.</speaker>
                  <p>And I, Sir, in the ſame, at the Suit of Mr. <hi>Wildman.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Mine! What means this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:97016:24"/>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Rum dun done! Broke like a Barrel of Figs! For Pity ſake, hear me but a Word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Be ſhort, Sir, I loſe time, and I've half a ſcore of your Neighbours to arreſt upon <hi>Change.</hi> Come, quick, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then, Gentlemen, I acknowledge my ſelf a Villain to my Nieces, and not much better to Madam <hi>Eugenia:</hi> You have made your ſelf, in part, Satisfaction; but a little Patience, I'll endeavour to compleat it. Here, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Honey; Why, <hi>Lettice? Lettice?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Lurch.</stage>
                  <p>Pray, give 'em a Call. <stage>(Exit <hi>Lurcher.</hi>)</stage> Mean while I take this Lady to my Wife, if ſhe can forget my Ingratitude, it will be ſome Comfort in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>isfortunes to ſay, I was once Juſt in my Life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>And to me to ſhare in 'em as I have done in your Proſperity. This, Sir, I hope, will convince you that I love.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Better half a Loaf, than no Bread.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe it, my Cinnamon-ſtick, tho' my Seeing and Hearing would be ſo impertinent as to convince me to the contrary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, Sir, in matters of Faith and Love, we ought never to truſt too much to the Senſes. Curioſity and Jealouſie are good for nothing but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Heriſie and Cuckoldom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, Sir, let the Simplicity of my Belief ſhew the vehemency of my Affection. Come, my All-ſpice, come. </p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Takes</hi> Eugen.<hi>aſide.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>If ſhe ben't as chaſte as her Neighbours, ſhe muſt feed upon <hi>Cantharides,</hi> and ſpend her Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money in Chocolate.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Aſide. Enter</hi> Lurcher <hi>with</hi> Hon. <hi>and</hi> Letitia.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And my Liberality be the mark of my Affection: In Conſideration of your Complaiſance, and of <hi>Eugenia</hi>'s Fortune, I freely forgive what Accompts may be between us; you ſhall have a Releaſe upon Demand, ſo my <hi>Leti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> conſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <p>With Pleaſure, Sir; and not only that, but I'll join with my Siſter to mollifie <hi>Trulove.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Entreaties, Ladies, would be needleſs; his Conſent is all I ſhall deſire in Requital.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you have it as freely as I can give it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>And there's Four: What bloody Doings will there be to Night!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>So this is pretty well, if it were not for thoſe Rogues the Bayliffs, that will blaze all about.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lurch.</speaker>
                  <p>Who I, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, you, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lurch.</speaker>
                  <p>Not I, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor I, Sir.</p>
                  <stage>Lurch. unmasking.</stage>
                  <p>You lie, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>the ſame.</stage>
                  <p>Nor I, Sir; by the Skie, Sir; let me die, Sir, if I lie, Sir: Why, Sir, I am no Mag-pye, Sir.</p>
                  <stage>Omnes praeter Tru.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>Lurcher!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſame; I fearing Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi> would have been in earneſt, took this Courſe, both to ſurprize you agreeably, and prevent further miſchief.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I muſt confeſs your Fate would have been ſomewhat ſevere, had you not been reaſonable— But I'm glad all's ended ſo fairly. As for them, a ſmall Spell will ſtop their Mouths, I don't doubt: Or at worſt, 'tis no ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger a thing for a Citizen to be a Cheat than a Cuckold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97016:24"/>
                  <speaker>Fick.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Gibing!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, Sir, Forgiveneſs and the Twenty Pound a Year, is all I ask; you ſhall find me hereafter ſo faithful to deſerve it— But as for this ſlip, I proteſt, Sir, what with Over care and Over-faſting, Idea's of Stocks, Pillories, Whipping-poſts, and Qualms of Conſcience, I was ſo tormented in the Spirit, that it run me almoſt mad. Blanch me like an Almond, Sir, if I remember any thing of the matter, but the Twenty Pound a Year aforeſaid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And the Civility-Money, <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I have been told ſince, that I rav'd mightily of the <hi>Barbadoes</hi> Fleet, and Bird in Hand.</p>
                  <stage>Omnes praeter Fick.</stage>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Friends of all ſides, I have yet Ten Thouſand Pound left me, out of which I'll allow you as I had determin'd, and put thee in preſent Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Hang Dirt, I was almoſt choak'd with it, and now I'm eas'd, methinks I'm as brisk as—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>Bottle-All, all Froth and Settlings.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>We ſhall ſee that preſently; I'll put your Agility to the Teſt for once. Strike up there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, pray Gentlemen, not ſo haſty, I want a Companion: I'll out and lure her, ſhe'll come to Fiſt in a trice, and there will be no ſport till I come, as the Man ſaid when he was going to be hang'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>That's but reaſonable, th' haſt been ſo inſtrumental in the laſt Comedy, 'twere Ingratitude to leave thee out, now its come to a Concluſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>to Lurch.</stage>
                  <p>And prithee do you in and haſten Supper: I ne'er cou'd work well on an empty Stomach.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Jon. Lurcher, <hi>ſeverally.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Mean time, if you pleaſe, I'll entertain you with a Song I lately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, which is both inſtructive, and ſuitable to this preſent occaſion. Here</p>
                  <stage>Enter two Muſicians</stage>
                  <p>here, ſing this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>By all means come; one Hawk, two Hums, and ſtart fair.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Whilſt the Song is a Singing, Enter</hi> Jon <hi>and</hi> Jenny.</stage>
               </sp>
               <div type="song">
                  <head>A SONG. To be Sung betwixt a Man and a Woman.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>WHY ſo cruel to your Lover?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh, the hidden Cauſe declare!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Twou'd be more cruel to diſcover</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What muſt bring you to Diſpair</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Men, like Salvage Beaſt's, Love ranging,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here to day, and there at night;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All our Fears are in your changing</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That your darling cheif Delight</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                     <l>All our Fears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ſo freſh a blooming Paſture.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Me for ever will encloſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You need fear no ſuch Diſaſter</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When I change, I'm ſure to loſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:97016:25"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He for ever will be kind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who in Love his profit finds.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                     <l>He for ever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But when Envious Age at loſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Has made all my Beauties bare;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then, like Land, that lies at waſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You'll not judge me worth your Care,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No man thinks that worth his Pains,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where's all Labour and no Gains.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                     <l>No man thinks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To convince you I'll be kind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I love where Time has no Controul,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Tis the Beauty of your Mind</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That has Charm'd my doating Soul:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As frail Beauty does decline,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Worth and Virtue briter ſhine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                     <l>As frail Beauty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="continuation_of_scene">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, once more all Friends; and to ſhew you how light what is paſt lies on my Heart, we'll have a Dance, and then—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jon.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Et caetera.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Fick.</stage>
                  <p>Sbud, Sir, what do you mean! Let's Sup orofs the Water, and Conſummate, or we ſhall ſet your Prentices ſo agog, they'll go out in a Party, and plunder all they meet, or run away from their. Aprons, and forfeit their Indentures.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>A Dance.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <p>Briskly perform'd! Honeſt Sir <hi>Fickle,</hi> Igad, thou'rt twenty Years youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than thou was't an Hour ago. Ah! this ſame Honeſty is Soveraign Geer! 'Tis the Beſt Hearts-Eaſe in Nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>True.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let thoſe that gluttle with their Store,</l>
                  <l>Strain'd from the Tears of Orphan's Blood o'th' Poor,</l>
                  <l>Suck on, and Leeches like, when over cramm'd—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fickle.</speaker>
                  <p>Crack in this World, and in the next be damn'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tru.</speaker>
                  <l>And thoſe that would be juſt, may Learn by thee,</l>
                  <l>That Honeſty's the ſureſt Policy</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:97016:25"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
